<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An exposicion in Englishe vpon the Epistle of .S. Paule, to the Colossians wherin the letter is purely declared, with many good exhortations to flee vice, and to take vertue, as shall appere clerely to the faithfull reader throughout all this epistle: written by Lancelot Ridley of Cantorbury. Anno salutis humanæ M.D.XLVIII.</title>
            <title>Exposicion in Englishe upon the Epistle of. S. Paule to the Colossians.</title>
            <author>Ridley, Lancelot, d. 1576.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1548</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 201 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 141 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10770</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21039</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104540</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840275</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840275</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4757</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10770)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4757)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 142:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An exposicion in Englishe vpon the Epistle of .S. Paule, to the Colossians wherin the letter is purely declared, with many good exhortations to flee vice, and to take vertue, as shall appere clerely to the faithfull reader throughout all this epistle: written by Lancelot Ridley of Cantorbury. Anno salutis humanæ M.D.XLVIII.</title>
                  <title>Exposicion in Englishe upon the Epistle of. S. Paule to the Colossians.</title>
                  <author>Ridley, Lancelot, d. 1576.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[280] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In aedibus Richardi Graftoni, typographi regii,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Excusum Londini :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno salutis humanæ M.D.LXVIII. [1548]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-R S⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Colossians --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4757:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4757:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>AN EXPOSICI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> in Engliſhe vpon the Epiſtle of. S. Paule, to the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſſians,
wherin the letter is pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely declared, with many good exhortacions to flee vice, and to take
vertue, as ſhall appere cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely to the faithfull reader throughout all this Epiſtle: written
by Lance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot Rid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley of Cantor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno ſalutis humanae. M.D.XLVIII.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>CVM PRIVILEGIO AD IMPRIMEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DVM SOLVM</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:4757:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4757:2"/>
            <head>¶The preface to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Race, mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and peace, from GOD oure father of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, bee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that loueth
<hi>GOD</hi> and his worde, and bee true ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters furth &amp; promoters of Gods holy Goſpell.
Amen.</p>
            <p>Becauſe the worde of God is the ſpirituall foode of our ſoule <hi>Matth. iiii.</hi> and as
neceſſary for the ſoule to feede it, as corporall food is to fede the body, ye more
neceſſarie, becauſe it feedeth the ſoule, a more plenteous thyng then is the body, and
geueth life eternall with GOD the father, whereas the foode of the body
<pb facs="tcp:4757:3"/> feedeth the body for a ſhort time and bryngeth not eternall life with God the
father. And this ſpirituall foode for the mooſte part lieth hid, in the letter of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
ſcripture, vnknowen to many that readeth ſcripture, becauſe thei dooe not vnderſtande that
thyng thei reade, although thei doo vnderſtande Engliſhe, and the ſcripture in many plain
pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, yet there bee in the holy ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, many darke places and hard ſentences to be
vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, whiche requireth more help then the bare texte in Engliſhe, either by diligente
ſearchyng oute the true tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlacion of that place, out of that toungue that it was firſt
written in, that is, out of the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew or the Greke tongue, in the whiche the holy ſcriptures
was
<pb facs="tcp:4757:3"/> firſt written: either by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paryng of one place of holy Scripture with another, and
expoundyng one place by another, or by dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent obſeruyng the circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and ſentences,
goyng before and commyng after, or by helpe of ſome learned aucthor, or god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly learned man in
holy ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, to whom more knowlege was geuen of GOD, bothe by great ſtudie, and alſo by
humble praier, made in faith for the ſame to God the aucthor of all wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and diuine
knowlege, by whiche meanes, the miſteries of holy ſcripture, bee knowen and ſhewed to man of
God.</p>
            <p>That the ſpirituall foode of this Epiſtle to the Colloſſians ſhould not be hid, but
parte of it made more ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and plain to the
<pb facs="tcp:4757:4"/> ſimple, not learned in the Latin toungue, I as one of the leaſt in learnyng
<hi>(quid em<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſca cum E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lephantis)</hi> haue ſette furthe this rude expoſicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in this
Epiſtle of ſainct Paule to the Colloſſians as it hath pleaſed God to geue me grace and
knowledge, as I did before in the Epiſtle of ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cte Paule to the Epheſians, and to the
Philippia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, ſtudiyng alway to profite all menne (if I could) and to hurt no man, as knoweth God
the iudge of conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and of all ſecrete thoughtes: And to excite other better learned then
I, and of more health of body then I haue, to applie their ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die &amp; wit, to ſet furth in
Engliſh ſome part of holy ſcripture, that the ſymple people might be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued more to read
the holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,
<pb facs="tcp:4757:4"/> and take more profite of theim, then thei doo now by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng onely of the letter, and
not vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding the true meanyng of that thei read, but rather rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to take it amiſſe,
then after the true ſence of the holy ghoſt: &amp; ſo by taking y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcriptures amiſſe,
commeth greate error and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, euil and prepoſterous iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, falſe truſtes and
vain hopes, and all for lacke of true knowlege of holy ſcriptures, as Chriſte ſaied to the
Sadduces <hi>Mat. xxii. Erratis, ignorantes ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pturas,</hi> you erre, not knowyng the
ſcriptures: So ignoraunce hath been and yet is, the cauſe of many errors and hereſies, and
that men runne into dampnacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iudgyng euill good, and good euil, ſwete ſoure, and ſoure
ſwete
<pb facs="tcp:4757:5"/> lighte darkenes, and darkenes light, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Prophete Eſai did threate woo
euerlaſtyng ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng. <hi>Eſaie .v.</hi> Woo bee to theim that call good euil, &amp; euill
good lighte darkenes, and darkenes lighte. &amp;c. So ignoraunce is yet y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſe of theſe
euils, although the Bible bee in Engliſhe, ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to euery man and woman to reade at their
pleaſures, to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor GOD, to edifie theimſelfes and other with all, ye, commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to bee
reade euery daie at Matins, Maſſe, and Euenſong, yet there remaineth great igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce,
corrupt iudgementes, blindzeales, not after the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege of God, and will remayne ſtill (excepte
I bee deceiued) and excepte the holy ſcriptures bee made more plainer to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lay peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb facs="tcp:4757:5"/> vnlearned, by ſome commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie, expoſicion, or annotacion, that the laie people
maie vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande the holy ſcriptures better and knowe the wil and pleaſure of GOD, by theim
opened and plainly declared.</p>
            <p>Therefore let ignoraunce the mother of al errors and hereſies ſuperſticion and Idolatrie,
bee clerely putte a waie, by knowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Gods holy ſacred word truely opened and declared, by
ſome expoſicion made by ſobre, ſadde and diſcrete learned men, that of holy ſcriptures
truly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, nothyng maie bee ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, but ſpirituall foode to feede the ſoule, or elles
I feare greatly, that many will gather poyſon for meate, and errors for truth, interpretyng the
holy ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures
<pb facs="tcp:4757:6"/> after their awne mynde and affeccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and not accordyng to the mynde of the holy
ghoſte, by whom it was written: But now I truſte that all ignorau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce Idolatrie, and
ſuperſticion, and blynde zeale, ſhall fall awaie by litle and litle, the cauſes of them
take awaie, and the true know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege of Gods woorde had, and ſuch Godly Homilies, ſhewyng ſo
muche Godly wiſedome, and true knowlege of neceſſary ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities for our ſaluacion, as was
neuer ſhewed before our daies, to the people of this realme: for the whiche, glory is to be geuen
to GOD, laude and praiſe to the kynges Maieſtie, and to his mooſte prudent and honorable
counſaill, that ſo tendereth the health and the ſaluacion of the
<pb facs="tcp:4757:6"/> people of this realme, that thei would haue al Idolatrie, ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticion, and
feined religion take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> awaie, and Chriſtes true honor and glory ſet furthe and groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that
all men mighte honor and worſhippe God truly, with that honor that he would be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nored,
appoynted not of manne but of God, in his holy ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res geuen to vs, to knowe God, to loue
God, and to feare God, to know our duetie to God, and to our neighbor, and to do it in deede the
better, accordyng to the will and pleaſure of God, to whom with the ſonne, and the holy
ghoſte be all honor and glory nowe and euer. <hi>AMEN.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="argument">
            <pb facs="tcp:4757:7"/>
            <head>¶ The argument of the Epiſtle:</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Apoſtle after his Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſalutacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth GOD thankes for theſe
Coloſſians, that thei were come to the true knowlege of Chriſt by the word of God, preached
to them by E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paphras, and had receiued faith hope, and charitie, as their wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes declared: he
praieth to God for their increaceme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al knowlege and Godly liuing, ſhewyng the
benefites of Chriſt the hed of the Churche, to theim and to all men, willyng theim to ſtand
ſure grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded vpon Chriſt the ſure foundacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and that thei would not ſhrynke from
Chriſt and his doctryne, by no craftie meanes of pſeudapoſtles that
<pb facs="tcp:4757:7"/> craftely went aboute to deceiue them by falſe doctrine, by ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticion of
Angelles, by Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy, by tradicions of men, by e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lementes of the worlde mixtyng the lawe with
the Goſpell, affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng Chriſt not to be onely the aucthor of healthe, nor the waie to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
father, to be made by Chriſt but by Angelles, ſuperſticiouſly obſeruyng the Sonne, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
Mone, and the Sterres. Therefore the Apoſtle, moniſheth theim to beware of theſe
pſeudapoſtles, and of their deceiuable doctrine and to ſticke to Chriſte and to his true
doctryne, as a ſufficient doctryne to bryng to health and ſaluacion, by Chriſt alone, with
out helpe of the Angelles, of the lawe, or of any other thyng. He exhorteth them to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre
Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes
<pb facs="tcp:4757:8"/> death and his reſurreccion, and to dye from ſynne and euill maners, and to walke
in a newe life, ſhewyng to diuerſe ſtates and degrees of men, their offices and dueties,
exhortyng them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly to feruent praiers, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng his Epiſtle (which he would ſhould bee
red aſwell to the Lao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicians, as to the Coloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians) with chriſtian ſalutacions,
wiſhyng the grace of of God euer to be with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>AMEN.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:4757:8"/>
            <head>¶ The firſt Chapiter to the Coloſſians.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>AVLE the apoſtle of Ieſu Chryſte by the wil of God and Timothe his brother, to the
Sanctes that are at Coloſſa and to the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full brethren in Chriſte: Grace bee with you,
and peace from God the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and our lorde Ieſus Chriſte.</p>
            <p>Sainct Paule the true Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle of Chriſte Ieſu, kepeth the maner vſed in Epiſtles
written: Firſt he ſaluteth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with a chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſalutacion, then he ſheweth
<pb facs="tcp:4757:9"/> his matter. And firſte he ſetteth his awne name, that the writter of this
Epiſtle might be knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Epiſtle more eſtemed and loued, and had in more auctho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of
al them, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it ſhould come and be red emonges them, and that thei ſhould knowe it to be
written of no falſe Apoſtle ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng his awne glory &amp; profite, but of a true Apoſtle of
Chriſte Ieſu, that aboue all thynges ſoughte Chriſtes glory, and the health and ſaluacion
of other.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Apoſtle of Ieſu Chriſte.) Paule here ſheweth his office y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he was called to,
that he was A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſent, not of man, but of God <hi>Gala. i.</hi> not to pleaſe ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but
God, ſent to preach, not mennes pleaſures phantaſies, or drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, inuencions, tradicions, or

<pb facs="tcp:4757:9"/> decrees of men, but he was the Apoſtle of Ieſu Chriſte, that he ſhould preache
Chriſte and his doctryne, puerly and ſyncerely, onely ſekyng the glory of God, and to
pleaſe GOD, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare Gods wil vnto the people by the pure preachyng of Gods worde, &amp;
by it to bryng to Chriſt and to eternall life, by true faith in Ieſu Chriſt: And in this that
Paule ſaied, he was the Apoſtle of Ieſu Chriſte, he reproueth all falſe Apoſtles, and
al them that ſtudie to pleaſe men more then God, that be more earneſt to ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>furthe mannes
lawe, then Gods lawe, &amp; more ſorer will puniſhe the tranſgreſſion of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes lawe then
the tranſgreſſion of Gods lawe, ye, this place reproueth al the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ſeketh more their
awne
<pb facs="tcp:4757:10"/> glory, pleaſure, and profite then the glory of Chriſte Ieſu, or the profit of
their neighbor: ye, this place co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dempneth all them that preacheth or ſpeaketh onely for their
bely ſakes, lookyng onely to themſelfes, and caryng for no man els, caring neither for God ne
man, ſo thei bee well themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fes, liuyng in al carnall pleaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res and deliciouſnes.</p>
            <p n="3">3 By the will of God.) Theſe wordes he addeth to ſhewe that he was an Apoſtle of
Chriſt, not by his awne will, merite, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruyng, but by the will of God and not of man,
that he ſhould geue all glory to GOD, for his vocacion and conuerſion from his naughtines, and
not to hym ſelf. And in theſe wordes, he tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth vs twoo thynges, to come
<pb facs="tcp:4757:10"/> of God, and not of man, the one is, that true Apoſtles come vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, not by will
of man, or whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> man thinketh it good, but by the will of God, that all laude and praiſe with
thankes, might bee geuen to God for true Apoſtles, ſent vnto vs to deliuer vs, from all fables,
lies, errors, hereſies, ſuperſticio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and Idolatrie, and to bryng vs into the waye of truthe,
in the whiche wee maye walke to life eternall. The other thyng is, to knowe the goodnes of God,
that will not ſuffre his electe people, to lacke faithfull preachers or miniſters, of Gods holy
will and pleaſure, for the whiche thynges, greate thankes are to be geuen to God.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Timothe his brother.) The Apoſtle in this ſalutacion, ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth
<pb facs="tcp:4757:11"/> with hym Timothe (whom he calleth brother, both by crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion and adopcion, and alſo
in ſettyng furthe of Gods worde) that theſe thynges he writeth to theſe faithfull
Colloſſia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, might bee regarded more and had in more aucthoritie, better beleued and better
loued of them all: for the true record of many faithful maketh muche with the ſimple Chriſtian,
and maketh men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue better, if many beare like recorde or witnes, of the thyng ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: ſo
ſainct Paule, although his worde ſhould haue been be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leued to bee true, without other witnes,
becauſe it was the word of the holy ghoſte, whiche ſpake by the mouthe of Paule. <hi>i. Cori.
xiii.</hi> Seke you ſaieth he, a profe of him that ſpeaketh in me, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che
<pb facs="tcp:4757:11"/> is Chriſt: yet he ioyneth with hym Timothe, that theſe Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſſians ſhould
the better beleue his wordes, eſteme them and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde theim better, ſo oft tymes dooth the
preacher or teacher of Gods worde, vſe the teſtimonie of other, that his wordes ſhould better
be beleued and eſtemed.</p>
            <p n="5">5 To the ſainctes &amp; to the faith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full in Chriſt, that are at Coloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa.) Nowe
he ſheweth to whom he wrote this Epiſtle, he wrote it to the ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ctes, that is, to the
faith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full in Chriſt Ieſu, ſuche the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſcripture calleth ſainctes, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though thei bee
a liue, liuyng in this world, and not canonized of the Biſhoppes of Rome, whiche wil none other
to be called ſain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctes, but ſuche as thei haue allo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed for ſainctes, well payed for
<pb facs="tcp:4757:12"/> their labors and paines, and yet ſome of theim allowed for ſain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctes, do not
appere to be ſainctes before God, ſanctified by Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes blood, and by true faithe in
Chriſte, and good woorkes ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued of God. So wee ſee that holy ſcripture calleth good men
liuyng in this worlde ſainctes, and theſe ſainctes he would wee ſhould, deſire to praye
for vs here, and we for them.</p>
            <p n="6">6 Grace bee to you and peace from GOD our father and our Lorde Ieſu Chriſt.) Here is
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, what thyng the Apoſtle deſired and wiſſhed to theim: he wiſſhed to them no
euil thynges but good thynges, not worldely honours or riches, pleaſures or volupteouſnes of
the fleſhe, not kyngdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s or high Empires, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnities,
<pb facs="tcp:4757:12"/> high honors, or promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions in the worlde, as carnall men deſire to their carnall
fren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, but he deſireth ſpirituall gooddes, as grace and fauor of God, peace with God in
their conſcience, whiche thinges com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth of God our father, &amp; not of our ſelfes, merites,
or of digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of our woorkes, but of God the father alone, and of our lord Ieſu Chriſt. In
this ſalutacion the apoſtle ſheweth, what maner of ſalutacion Chriſtians ſhould vſe,
one to another in their wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynges, and what thynges thei ſhould deſire, and of whom.</p>
            <p>Wee geue thankes to GOD and the father of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, alwaye for you when we
<pb facs="tcp:4757:13"/> praye, for we haue heard your faith in Ieſu Chriſt and your charitie towar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des
all ſainctes, for the hope layed vp for you in heauen.</p>
            <p>Now the Apoſtle beginneth to ſhewe the cauſe wherefore he wrote to them, and firſt of
all, he geueth thankes to god for their hope and charitie, and other gif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of God, geuen to
theſe Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſſia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, onely of gods mere mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and goodnes, deſiryng God to encreaſe
theſe gyftes, euery daie more and more in them. By this example wee bee taught to geue thankes to
god, for his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefites geuen to other, and to be glad with other for theſe diuine
<pb facs="tcp:4757:13"/> giftes, and to deſire theim to bee euery daie more &amp; more increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. And in
theſe woordes he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proueth them, that thanketh not God for his holy gyftes, geuen to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and to
other, ye, he repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that enuie Gods good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in other, and be ſory that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be
riche, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nyng, learned, or haue more knowlege then thei, ſuch there is many now a daies, whom it
greueth muche, to ſe ſo greate knowlege of Gods holy worde and truthe, ſhewed to the worlde
as now is, for the whiche thyng, thei ſhould geue thankes to GOD for it: as here the holy ghoſt
teacheth vs, and not to be ſory for it, or to murmure or ſpurne agaynſte the pricke, as many
wiſſhyng all theſe new me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the newe doctrine (as thei call
<pb facs="tcp:4757:14"/> it, when it is in verie deede the olde doctryne of Chriſte, and of his Apoſtles)
in a fire or at the deuil, condempnyng themſelfes to the deuill and to hell fire, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng or
thynkyng Chriſtes do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine error and hereſy, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dempnyng it for euill, whiche is good and
wholeſome, and true doctrine able to ſaue our ſoules. <hi>Iacob .i.</hi> Let menne therefore
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware, and condempne not truthe for falſed, and call not good euil or euill good, light
darkenes, &amp; darkenes light, leaſt wo euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyng fall vpon them, for ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng and
calling. Take hede you ignoraunt men, that you fal not into this daungier of eternall dampnacion,
threatened by the Prophete. <hi>Eſaye .v.</hi> to all theim that call good, euill, &amp; euil
good,
<pb facs="tcp:4757:14"/> light, darkenes, and darkenes light, ſwete, ſower, &amp; ſower ſwete, &amp;c.
Learne that the holy ghoſte in Paule, moueth vs in our pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers, to geue thankes to GOD for his
benefites geuen to vs, &amp; ſpecially for the gyfte of faithe, and of charitie. Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly, he
ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth what is the office of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians to do, when thei here faith and charitie geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to
men of god, that thei ſhould geue tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes to God for them. Thirdly, we ſe the office of faithe
and of charitie: a true faith hath charitie annexed, &amp; worketh by charitie at all
op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie, geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in tyme conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: charitie ſheweth her ſelf, by helpyng and releuyng
the poore faithfull: Finally faith &amp; chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, bee the twoo chief thinges of Chriſtes
religion, for the whiche
<pb facs="tcp:4757:15"/> we ſhould geue tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes to God, as giftes moſt neceſſary for our ſaluacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
without the whiche, we cannot pleaſe god, nor be ſaued.</p>
            <p n="2">2 For wee haue heard of your faithe in Ieſu Chriſte, &amp; of your Charitie to the
poore ſainctes.) Here is declared the cauſe why Paule gaue thankes to God, it was that he heard
their faith in Chriſte Ieſu, and their charitie to the poore, to be ſpred abrode, for vertue
vſed cannot bee hid long, but it wil ſhewe it ſelf, ſo a true and a liuely faith cannot be
hid lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, but it will burſt vp into good woorkes: as here Paule heard their faithe, and yet
faithe cannot bee heard nor ſene (for it is an inuiſible gifte of God) nor yet ſhewed, except
it ſhewe it ſelf by good workes, whiche declare
<pb facs="tcp:4757:15"/> faithe, and ſheweth where it is, that it may be knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and heard where it is, for a
true faithe in God, is not idle or dedde: in that he nameth firſte faithe, and then Charitie, he
ſheweth that faithe muſte goo before charitie, or els that woorke of Charitie, that ſpryngeth
not out of faith, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth not God, for it is vnpoſſible to pleaſe GOD without faith.
<hi>Heb. ii.</hi> Faith is towardes God, charitie to God &amp; to our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor: charitie doth
conſiſt in wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes and dedes, &amp; in ferue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tnes of hart &amp; mynd, to worke when po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and
habilitie will not ſerue, nor is power geuen to worke.</p>
            <p n="3">3 For the hope laied vp for you in heauen.) This place is of au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cthors diuerſly
expounded, ſome make it agre with that that goth
<pb facs="tcp:4757:16"/> before, after this maner: Wee haue heard of your faith, and of your Charitie to the
poore ſain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctes, &amp; faithfull chriſtians, doen to theim for no other cauſe, but for
Chriſtes ſake, not lookyng for any praiſe, glory, or profite, to you, of manne, for theſe
woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, but onely for Gods ſake, and becauſe of hope of immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talitie, and glory with God,
that you truſted to bee partaker of, not for the worthines of youre woorke, or almoſe dooen to
the poore by you, but onely of the promiſe of God, whoſe free gifte is life euerlaſtyng, and
not for the worthines or dignitie, of any worke or dede, doen by any mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall man. And this ſence
ſaincte Peter. <hi>i. Peter .i.</hi> dooth appere to allowe: ſaiyng thus. Bleſſed bee
<pb facs="tcp:4757:16"/> God, and the father of our lorde Ieſu Chriſte, whiche after his greate mercie,
hath regenerated vs, into a liuely hope, by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurreccion of Ieſu Chriſte from death. So
for hope of eternall life, we muſt do good woorkes, ſurely truſtyng to come to that life,
onely of Gods mercie and goodnes, and not of dignitie or worthines of workes, for the fre gift of
Gods life eternal. <hi>Roma. vi.</hi> Other referreth this place, to the woordes that goeth before,
that is to theſe: Wee geue than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes to GOD for you, that you haue not put your truſt &amp;
hope, in worldly thynges, or in corru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptible riches, but in heauenly thynges, lokyng more for
hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly treaſure, then any world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dignities or riches, onely to
<pb facs="tcp:4757:17"/> be geuen to you of Gods mercy, for Chriſtes ſake, for whom you ſuffre muche
trouble, and aduer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſitie in the worlde, that ye might be partaker of Chriſtes glory in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
accordyng to that whiche is promiſed, that if wee ſuffre with Chriſt, we ſhal reigne with
hym. <hi>Rom. viii.</hi> Whiche you ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely truſt and hope for, nothyng doubtyng, but GOD will
per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme his promes, and for that hope, you willyngly, gladly, and of loue, ſhewe Charitie to
the poore, and helpeth them to your power, not lokyng for a reward of men, but onely of god. Some
other by hope, vnderſtandeth GOD and his glory hoped for whiche glory is called hope, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
it is ſure keped, as Iob ſaieth .xix. This hope is put in
<pb facs="tcp:4757:17"/> my boſome, that is the thyng lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked for by hope. <hi>i. res ſperata.</hi> O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
ſome thinketh by hope, may be vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d God alone whiche is the rewarder of all that hope in
him, and will reward al good workes dooen for his ſake, loue or commaundement alone, with<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>out all
other reſpect, truſtyng to Gods promiſes. And here pera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture ſome will aſke a
queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: whether we ſhould do good deedes, for hope of eternall life, or no? To this
queſtion maie be made anſwer thus, that we muſt do good workes, appoynted vs of GOD to do,
principally for God and for his loue, becauſe we are his creatures, made to do good woorkes, and
to walke in them, lookyng for that rewarde that he hath bothe frely promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,
<pb facs="tcp:4757:18"/> will frely geue, accordyng to his promiſe, to all the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that with a ſure faith and
conſtaunt hope, do perſeuer and continue in the wayes of the Lorde, kepyng his commaundementes.
Seconde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for the rewardes ſake prom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vs of God, we muſt do good workes, ſo that in
all oure wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, we muſte moſte chiefly and aboue all thynges, looke to the will, pleaſure,
loue, and glory of GOD. Thirdely, to our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite, glorie, or life to come, wee muſte ſo in all
our workes loke for the glory of God, that ſkarce once wee ſhould remembre oure profit or glory
to come: for if we ſeke more our awne profite and glory, then the glory of God, we bee but
mercemarii hirelynges, vnworthy that glory &amp; immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall
<pb facs="tcp:4757:18"/> life, in the worlde to come with Chriſt, whiche glory, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not bee bought by woorkes
of vs, but we muſte come to it onely of the free gifte of God, and of his mercie and grace.
<hi>Roma. vi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of the whiche before you harde, by the true word of the Goſpel whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is come to you, as to
all the worlde, and as it fructifieth throughout y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole worlde, ſo it doeth emonges you,
ſince that daie you heard and haue knowen, the grace of God by the truthe. And as you haue
learned of Epaphras, our welbelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
<pb facs="tcp:4757:19"/> ſeruaunt, whiche is for you a faithfull mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of Chriſt, which ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed to
vs youre loue in the ſpirite.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle ſhewed before, their mercifulnes to the poore ſainctes, and faithfull in
Chriſt for hope of reward, layed vp for them in heauen: now he ſheweth how thei gotte that
hope, that it was by the true preachyng of the Goſpell, whiche Epaphras preached vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.
Learne here how hope of heauenly rewarde, and life commeth, that it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth by preachyng of the
Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell of Chriſte, whiche is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led here, the true woorde of the Goſpell, and the truthe
it ſelf. If hope of heauenly rewarde, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth
<pb facs="tcp:4757:19"/> by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preaching of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, as it dooeth in deede, then what hope of heauenly
rewarde can thei haue, where as the word of the Goſpel is not peached? or what hope of heauenly
life haue thei, that will not here the worde of God preached? That contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pneth and deſpiſeth
it, and eſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth it no better, then a fooliſhe tale of Robyn Hoode, Guye of Warwicke, or Beuis
of Hamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, ſurely no hope at al. Learne here alſo, how neceſſary a thyng for our
ſaluacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, is the preachig of Gods worde, that without it, ſeldom be geuen, faithe, hope or
charitie. For faithe commeth by hearyng, &amp; hearyng by the word of God. <hi>Roma. x.</hi> And
hope com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth by the true woorde of the Goſpell, as here is ſhewed, and
<pb facs="tcp:4757:20"/> Charitie ſpryngeth out of true faithe, and ſure hope. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle garniſheth
the Goſpell, with his due laude and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendacion callyng it the true woorde, that deceiueth no
man, &amp; the truthe it ſelf, that none ſhould doubt of it but that euery man that loueth the
truth, ſhould be glad to here the Goſpell, preached or taught, becauſe it is the truth, and
put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth away all falſed, lies, errors, and hereſies.</p>
            <p n="2">2 And as it fructifieth through<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>out the whole worlde, ſo it doeth emo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges you.) He
ſaith, the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell to fructyfye and encreaſe throughout all the whole world as emo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
that thei ſhould more reioyſe and be glad, as all good menne reioyſeth, when the Goſpell
gooeth forwardes and
<pb facs="tcp:4757:20"/> fructifieth, and euill men be ſory that the Goſpell is purely and ſincerely
preached, receiued, and beleued: but thei geue thankes to God for it. Here we learne to be our
office, to bee glad to here the Goſpell of God, to bee prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched ſincerely, and to geue God
thankes for it.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Sence that daie you harde and haue knowen the grace of God, by the truthe.) He ſheweth
how long the Goſpell, hath fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctefied emo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges them: euen ſence that daie, thei heard the grace
of God, and knewe it by the true preachyng of the Goſpell. And here we maie lerne diuerſe good
leſſons: Firſt, that faithe is ſure and firme, that commeth by the worde of truthe.
Secondly, that the ſincere preachyng of the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell,
<pb facs="tcp:4757:21"/> not to bee vain or fruſtrate, although it is not knowen, how it dooth fructifie,
and in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at the firſt, to hym that preacheth, yet it goeth not away in vain, as the Prophet
Eſaie ſaieth. Thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dely, the benefites or the grace of God, bee knowen by the pure preachyng of
y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Goſpell of truth and not of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or of a multitude of men, that call theimſelfes the
church, when it maie be doubted of, whether thei bee any membre of the churche or no, ſeyng their
workes be ſo contrary, to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes true Churche. Fourthely, learne that the grace of GOD, and
his benefites is ſurely kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen, by the truth of gods word. And here it ſemeth, that ſaincte
Paule would haue vs, to learne and know Chriſt, and the grace
<pb facs="tcp:4757:21"/> of God, by no other thyng, but by the truth, and to iudge euery thyng, by the truthe
of Goddes holy worde, for the holy ghoſt is the moſte ſureſt declarer of hym<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelf. Learne
alſo that Chriſt, and the grace of GOD, and Gods benefites is there vnknowen, where as the
woorde of God is not preached, and how can God be loued, feared, or dread, where as he is not
knowen? Or howe can there be any health, or eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſaluacion, where as is no loue, feare, ne
dread of God? And if it bee life eternall (as it is in deede, witnes ſainct Ihon. <hi>xvii.</hi>)
to knowe GOD the father, and his ſonne Ieſus Chriſte, then it muſte nedes followe, that it
is death, not to knowe God the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and his ſonne Ieſus Chriſt
<pb facs="tcp:4757:22"/> and Gods benefites to vs, for Chriſtes ſake, theſe benefites be vnknowen, where
as the worde of God is not taught, therfore ſe how neceſſarie it is for oure ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to
haue the worde of God plenteouſly preached, and truly taught, that God might be kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, loued,
feared, and dread, and his wil and pleaſure fulfilled of al men. Finally, learne here how farr be
thei from health, life, and ſaluacion, that will not here the worde of God, but contempneth to
here it, ye, diſpiſeth it, and the true preachers of it, ſlaunders, backebites, perſecutes,
and as muche as in them lieth, goeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute to let, hinder, and vtterly to ſtoppe and quenche
the word of God, and to bryng to deathe, the faithfull miniſters of Gods
<pb facs="tcp:4757:22"/> holy worde, the neceſſarie foode of our ſoule, and yet of the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunt, it is
thought poyſon, and death of the ſoule: God turne the hartes of ſuche, and make theim his
ſeruauntes.</p>
            <p n="4">4 And as you haue learned of Epaphras, our welbeloued ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunt, whiche is for you a
faith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful ſeruaunt of Chriſt.) Now he ſheweth who it was, that firſte preached the
goſpel, to theſe Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſſians, not Paule hymſelf, but it was Epaphras, a diſciple of
Paules, and a true miniſter of Chriſte, in the ſincere preachyng of Chriſtes Goſpel, and
this E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paphras, returnyng agayne to Paule, in priſon for the Goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les ſake, ſhewed to
Paule of the faith, hope, and of the charitie of theſe Coloſſians, for the whiche
<pb facs="tcp:4757:23"/> thynges, Paule comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, not that thei ſhould bee proude, but that thei
ſhould increaſe dai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly more and more, in theſe holy vertues and giftes, with tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes to God.
<hi>Na<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> uirtus laudata creſcit.</hi> Vertue commendeth increaſes. Learne here what
ſeruauntes, or chapilaines, ſhould Biſhoppes haue aboute the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſurely ſuche as this
Epaphras was to Paule, one that loued his Maſter, in al goodnes, and Godlines, and for the truth
ſake: a man that loued God and his woorde, that was glad, when he hard the worde of God, to bee
purely preached a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brode, and to bryng furth God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fruites, as faithe, hope, and charitie, and of
greate gladnes, ſhewed theſe fruictes to other, that other mighte glorifie God,
<pb facs="tcp:4757:23"/> and geue thankes to GOD, for the Goſpell preached, &amp; to make other to followe
theſe Coloſſia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in faithe, hope, and charitie, and in other Godly vertues. I feare me that
all Biſhoppes and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble men, hath not alwaie ſuche ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, or chapilaines about them and
with theim, that be fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorers and louers, of Gods ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly word, but rather enemies and aduerſaries
to it, ye, haters of it, ſlaunderers, liers, and euill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porters of faithfull miniſters of
Gods woorde, reportyng ſuche euil vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> preachers, as the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers neuer did ſpeake, nor
thoughte, ye, parauenture ſuche thynges, as true preachers hath and dooth, euer abhorre and
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt: Ye, parauenture ſuche thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, as the preachers hath ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb facs="tcp:4757:24"/> again, and forbiddyng to be doen, ſpoke or thought: and ſuch euill toungues,
liyng to pleaſe their Maiſters, by their falſe li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng hath broughte, many good and faithfull
preachers, to bee had in hatered, and euil eſtemed of many Biſhoppes, and noble men, whiche of
ignoraunce hath perſecuted, ye, parauenture put to death faithfull miniſters of Chriſtes
Goſpell, whoſe innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t bloud, ſhed for Chriſtes Goſpel ſake, God will puniſhe,
excepte thei repent and amende, and to cal to God for mercy and grace. Therefore lette biſhoppes,
and al noble men, and noble women, bee not haſtie of credence, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, euill or preachers,
and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhe their ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, to beware what thei reporte of preachers,
<pb facs="tcp:4757:24"/> and that thei reporte no other thyng of them, then that thei can proue by honeſt
menne, as thei would haue their maſters fauor or profites by their Maiſters, then ſhould
euill reportes, and falſe ſlau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders, ceaſe of true prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of Goddes woorde, then ſhould
faithefull Miniſters of Chriſtes Goſpell bee knowen, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the falſe miniſters, and true
preachers fauored and eſtemed of men, as thei bee worthie, then ſhould God bee the more
glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, his word better truſted and beleued, God better knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and loued, and ſo come into
health, &amp; to eternall ſaluacion by Chriſt, whereas now the contrary doen and ſuffred,
many worketh their awne and euerlaſting death and dampnacion, perſecutyng Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes
<pb facs="tcp:4757:25"/> faithfull Miniſters, thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng parauenture, then to do a ſacrifice pleaſaunt to
God, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thei do perſecute Chriſte, in his membres, as Paule did, before he was conuerted, as
it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten. <hi>Actes. ix. Philip. iii.</hi> I praie God thei maye be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerted with Paule,
&amp; to plaie Paules parte, that thei maie be preachers, tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, and ſetters furth of Gods
holy woorde, as earneſt as euer holy ſainct Paule was, and ſeke Gods glory, and the
ſaluacion of other, as Paule did.</p>
            <p>Therfore, and we ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce the daie wee harde, haue not ceaſſed do praye for you, &amp; to
deſire that you might bee fulfilled with the knowlege of his will
<pb facs="tcp:4757:25"/> in all ſapience and wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, &amp; ſpirituall vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandyng, that ye
mighte walke worthelye, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyng God in all thynges, fructifiyngi al good wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes, and
increaſing in the knowlege of God, ſtren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gthened with all ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth after the power of the
glory of hym, to all tolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and pacience, with ioye, geuyng thankes to the father.</p>
            <p>Nowe the Apoſtle goeth for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, in his praier he had bego<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and ſaieth: that he geueth
than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes to God, and hath not ceaſed to praie to God for theim, that
<pb facs="tcp:4757:26"/> thei might be fulfilled, with all godly wiſedo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; ſpiritual know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege, that
thei might walke wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily, pleaſyng God, and bryng furthe all good workes, increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyng in the
knowlege of God. In this praier, the Apoſtle tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth vs, one to praie for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and to geue
tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes to God for his benefites geuen to men, and ſpecially for faith, hope, and charitie, as
here Paule did. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, here we maie learne, not to ceaſſe from praier, to God for other.
Thirdely, this place tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth vs, what wee ſhould deſire to other, aboue al thynges, ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
this thyng, that thei mighte haue knowlege of God, and of his benefites, whiche is ſo
neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, that no man can bee ſaued
<pb facs="tcp:4757:26"/> without it. Fourthly, hereis ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed, for what ende and purpoſe Godly wiſedo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
is neceſſary, that it is ordeined for this ende, that men ſhould walke worthily, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordyng
to their vocacion, euery man in his ſtate and degre, that he is called vnto of God. Alway
ſtudiyng to pleaſe God, and not hymſelf, the worlde, or the fleſhe, the multitude of the
people, but God alwaye. For he that ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth to pleaſe men, high or lowe, hymſelf or the
worlde, he cannot pleaſe God. <hi>Non poteſt quiſqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> duobus dominis ſeruire:</hi> No man
can pleaſe twoo Maſters, of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary affeccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and myndes: Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, Godly wiſedome is
ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated, that men ſhould fructifie in all good workes, that is: doo all good workes, whiche
thyng
<pb facs="tcp:4757:27"/> thei ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not do, till thei be taught which are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good woorkes that pleaſeth God,
&amp; how thei ſhould do the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and for whoſe ſake, &amp; for what ende good workes ſhould
be dooen. This place reproueth al the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that bee ſory that there is ſo muche knowlege, of gods
ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly worde, had emonges the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple as is, ſaiyng: it was a merie worlde, when euery manne,
wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, or child, could not prate of Gods word, and ſence that time there was neuer no mery
world, curſſyng, and banning, and wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyng to the Deuill, ſuche as brought in this newe
learnyng, as thei call it: ſo by theimſelfes you maie ſee, and by their awne wordes it is
plain, thei cal gods woorde newe learnyng, and the preachers and ſetters furth of it
<pb facs="tcp:4757:27"/> heretiques, worthy fire and a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotte to burne them, ſaiyng: thei would go .xx.
mile bare foote, to burne ſuche heretiques, ſo by i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnoraunce, thei ſpeake &amp; worke their
awne dampnacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And as Chriſte ſaied to the Sadduces. <hi>Math. xxii.</hi> So maie men ſaie
to them, <hi>erratis, ignorantes ſcripturas,</hi> you erre, and fal into errors and hereſies,
deceiuyng your ſelfes and other, becauſe you are igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunte of the holy ſcriptures:
al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thoughe you call other hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques and deceiuers, yet you bee the heretiques in deede, and
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuers of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people, worthy that puniſhement, that you wiſſhe to other, excepte you
repent and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mende, and reforme your iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, wordes, and deedes, and call to God for mercy
and grace
<pb facs="tcp:4757:28"/> and ſeke for better, &amp; more truer knowlege in Gods veritie and truthe, and haue
a better mynde to it, and to the true preachers and ſetters furthe of it. This place alſo
reproueth, all the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that do abuſe Godly knowlege, and vſe it for their carnall libertie,
ſenſuall pleaſure, worldly honor and dignitie, eaſe, reſte, profite, and for their belie
ſakes, ſuch do not ſerue God, but their belies, whoſe ende is deathe, and their glory here,
ſhalbee in tyme to come, to their confuſion, ſhame, and euerlaſtyng death. <hi>Phili.
iii.</hi> if thei do not repent and amend, for Godly wiſedom is geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that thei ſhould ſerue
and pleaſe god and not theimſelfes, or their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies. And ſuche bely beaſtes, bee the
cauſe, that the worde of God
<pb facs="tcp:4757:28"/> is euill ſpoken on, becauſe thei doo abuſe their knowlege, and turneth it to
their carnall plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, proffites, or glory. But ſuche, let theim put awaie igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce, and
take vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wiſedome, and knowlege, and ſtudy to liue after Godly know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege, or els
their knowlege, ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be to their more condempnacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as Luke ſayeth, the ſeruaunte knowyng
the will of his Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and not doyng it, is worthy greate puniſhement, and many plagues to
bee laied vpon his backe.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Fructifiyng in all good wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes.) Godly wiſedo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> here deſired willeth vs to fructify
in al good woorkes, that is: It would wee ſhould bryng furth, al maner of good workes, &amp; not
one worke
<pb facs="tcp:4757:29"/> alone, as ſome there bee, that thynke it ſufficient for theim, to haue doen one
good woorke, as ſome to haue builded a Chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try ſome an Abbay, ſome a houſe of Fryers,
ſome a Nunnery, ſome an Hermitage, ſome a Guylde, ſome a Candle, ſome a Torche, euer to
burne in ſuche a churche before this Image, or that I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, whiche be workes not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded of
God, nor yet requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of man, to the which, no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of rewarde, is promiſed of God: but
Godly knowlege, take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of ſcripture, teacheth me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not onely to do one good worke, but to do
all maner of good workes appoynted in holy ſcripture, to be doen. This place doeth ſeme to
declare, that holy ſcripture is able to ſhewe, all maner of good
<pb facs="tcp:4757:29"/> workes, &amp; that there is no worke to bee called good, excepte it bee commended,
and alſo commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to be doen in holy ſcripture. And this ſaiyng of ſainct Paule
reproueth thoſe men, that thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the holy ſcriptures, cannot teache all neceſſarie
truthes, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient for our ſaluacion: &amp; thoſe men ſainct Paule <hi>.ii. Timothe.
iii</hi> reproueth, ſaiyng: the holy ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures to be able, to inſtruct me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in
righteouſnes, that he maie be made perfite, and ready to do al maner of good workes: He
exce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pteth none. If y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ghoſt had thought other workes, then ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſcripture ſpeaketh
of, to haue been neceſſary for our ſaluacion and that ſuche workes of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie ought
to be doen, he would not haue ſaid (I thinke) the holy
<pb facs="tcp:4757:30"/> ſcripture to inſtructe vs, and to make vs ready to doo all good workes.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Increaſyng in knowlege.) The Apoſtle would wee ſhould bee fulfilled, not onely
with all wiſedome, and ſpirituall vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandyng, but alſo he would we ſhould increaſe
in knowlege, &amp; euery daie bee better and better learned: and haue more &amp; more knowlege of
Gods holy worde. Here we maie ſe, that euery man bee he neuer ſo well learned be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, yet he
maie learne, more wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedome and knowlege, of Gods holy worde. Ye, we ſe it is euery mannes
duetie, euery daie to learne of Gods holy word, more and more knowlege, and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe in the
ſame. This place ſharpely reproueth all men that
<pb facs="tcp:4757:30"/> wil not learne knowlege of god<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des holy woorde, and ſpecially prieſtes, that will
not learne, but rather ſpend their tyme idlely, at Cardes or Diſe, then thei will loke vpon the
newe Teſtament, or of the old Teſtament, and wil bee no better learned, then thei wer the
firſt daie, thei wer made prieſtes: Ye, this place reproueth all them, that will not heare
ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, Lectures of diuinitie in Engliſhe, or in Latyn, or in that tongue thei vnderſtand,
ye, this place co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dempneth all them, that thynke it is enough for the rude people, to ſaie their
<hi>Pater noſter,</hi> and <hi>Aue Maria,</hi> and the <hi>Credo,</hi> and with them to bee
contented, and needeth to learne no more knowlege, when ſaincte Paule would we ſhould, euery
daie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe
<pb facs="tcp:4757:31"/> more and more, in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege, and ſpiritual wiſedom: and as thei increaſe in
knowlege of God, ſo he would thei ſhould in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe in Godlines, &amp; in vertue, that thei
might be ſtrengthened with al Godly power &amp; ſtrength able to beare all aduerſitie
paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently, geuyng thankes to God in their ſtate, liuyng vprightly in their vocacion.</p>
            <p>whiche hath made vs able to the felowſhip of ſainctes in light, whiche hath deliuered vs
from the power of darkenes, and hath tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlated vs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the kyngdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his wel beloued ſonne,
by whom we haue redempcio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and
<pb facs="tcp:4757:31"/> by his blood, forgeuenes of ſynnes.</p>
            <p>Now the Apoſtle turneth hym to the chief matter and cauſe, for the which he wrote this
Epiſtle, that it was to ſhewe health, and eternall life, to be geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to vs all frely, by
Chriſt, without reſpect, merite, or dignitie of our woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, or of any thyng that is in vs.
And firſt, he ſheweth part of the benefites, that we haue recei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued by Chriſt: Firſte, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
when we wer vnable to thinke, to will or to do any good worke or deede, he made vs able, and did
geue vs power to thynke, will, and do good. Of the whiche wee maie learne, that all power to
thynke, will, or do good, commeth not of our ſelfes, but of GOD, the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cthor of all goodnes, as
ſaincte
<pb facs="tcp:4757:32"/> Iames ſaieth. <hi>Iames .i.</hi> Second, we be made partakers of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritaunce,
of ſainctes in lighte, that is: of that heauenly inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce, that holy ſainctes be of, in
light and in glory, and thus wee bee made, not by our ſelfes, but by Chriſt, when we were
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, farr fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it, hauyng no right ne title, to chalenge or clayme, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heauenly glory, for our
inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce. Now by Chriſt we haue right title, to claime it for our in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>heritau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. He addeth
in light, as he would ſaie, our inheritaunce was before in darkenes, now it is in light, of the
father of light, by Chriſte. Thirdly, God hath deliuered vs, from the power of darkenes, and
tranſlated vs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his welbeloued ſonne, Ieſus Chriſte, for whoſe
<pb facs="tcp:4757:32"/> ſake alone, we wer deliuered fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all power of darkenes, that is of the deuill, the
aucthor of darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and from al workes of dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenes, as from ſynne, death, hell and from
euerlaſtyng dampna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion: alſo the father of heauen, hath take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs awaie fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenes, and
blyndnes of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce, of Gods holy word, and brought vs into his truthe, and into the lighte of
the veritie, of Gods holy woorde, now openly preached and ſhewed, thankes be to God. We wer
ſome tymes as ſaieth ſainct Paule. <hi>Ephe. ii.</hi> The children of the Ire of God and of
darkenes, but wee are now made the children of God, by adopcio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and of light, as chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of
light, let vs walke in all iuſtice, veritie, and goodnes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:4757:33"/> wee were in darkenes, and did walke in darkenes, in much Idolatrie, ſuperſticion,
and fei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned holines, thynkyng that wee pleaſed God very well, when we highly diſpleaſed God,
commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng Idolatrie, and muche ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſticion, goyng &amp; wanderyng about, from one Image, to
ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, puttyng truſte and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in them, &amp; ſekyng health of body, or of ſoule,
of ded ſtockes &amp; ſtones, wherein was no health nor holines: but from this Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie and
darkenes, God hath deliuered vs, and tranſlated vs, into his Kyngdome, and made vs iunct heires
with Chriſte, to bee partakers of his glory, and that not for our merites or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruynges, but
onely for the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites of Chriſte Ieſu, that ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb facs="tcp:4757:33"/> for vs: By whom wee are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demed, from all captiuitie and thraldom of the deuill,
fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> death or hell: thus Chriſte Ieſus, oure onely ſauior and redemer, payed that rau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſom
for vs, that we wer neuer able to paie <hi>.i. Timothe. ii.</hi> And by Chriſtes bloud ſhed for
vs wee haue remiſſion, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geuenes of our ſynnes: and not by the Biſhop at Romes
Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons, bulles, or indulgence, pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimages to Peter of Rome, or to Iames at Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poſtella,
Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Becket at Cantorbury, or to Etheldrede at Ely, the Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of our Lady at Walſyngha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or
at Ipſwyche, or to any ſuche like pilgrimage, erected and ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped for filthy lucre ſake, to
the diſhonor of God, &amp; to the greate hurt of them, that truſted health
<pb facs="tcp:4757:34"/> ſaluacion, or life, in ſuche pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, I will not ſpeake of the greate
Idolatrie, there commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Note that remiſſion of ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, is onely by Chriſtes bloud,
and by nothyng els. <hi>ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>guis Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti nos mundauit, ab omni iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate. .i. Io<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>is .i.</hi>
The bloud of Chriſt hath waſhed vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our ſynnes. and ſaincte Ihon. <hi>Apocalipſis
.i.</hi> ſaieth, that Chriſt hath waſſhed vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our ſynnes, in his bloud, ſo
redempcion and remiſſion of ſynne, is onely by Chriſte.</p>
            <p>whiche is the Image of the inuiſible God, firſt begotten before all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, for by hym
wer all thynges created, whiche are in heauen &amp; in yearth
<pb facs="tcp:4757:34"/> able to bee ſene, or not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to bee ſene, whether thei be thrones, or
Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippes, or pollicies, or Poteſtates, all thynges by hym, and in hym, are created, and he
is aboue al thynges, and all thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges are by hym.</p>
            <p>Nowe the Apoſtle deſcribeth very plainly, what Chriſt is, by whom we haue redempcion, and
by whoſe bloud we are purged, from our ſynnes. He ſaieth that Chriſte is the liuely Image
of God the father, that cannot bee ſene of corporall iyes, and that he is the brightnes, of the
glory of the father, and the true image of the ſubſtaunce of the father,
<pb facs="tcp:4757:35"/> 
               <hi>Hebre .i.</hi> That is, he is equall to the father in deitie, power and
ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and in all thynges as he is God. <hi>Phili. i.</hi> To the which Chriſt, the
father hath geuen all thynges, and in hym are layed vp, all the treaſure of the wiſedo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the
father. This Chriſt, is the firſt begotten of all creatures, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is, he was before all
creatures: for the ſonne was in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng, &amp; the ſonne was with God and God was the
ſonne, and all thynges was made by hym, and w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out hym was nothyng made, <hi>Ihon. i.</hi> And
this ſonne, was in glory with the father, before the world was made, as ſainct Iho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaieth
.xvii. ſpeakyng of Chriſt. Whiche ſpeaketh to his father after this ſorte. Father, glorifie
me with the ſame glory, that I
<pb facs="tcp:4757:35"/> had, before the worlde was crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Chriſt is called the firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſonne
of the father, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was the firſt borne, and other borne after hym, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
he was before all other creatures, and by who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, all other was created, and hath their bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng,
whether thei bee in heauen, as Angelles, Archa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gelles, thro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and other Poteſtates and powers,
or thei be in the yearth, in the water, or vpon the yearth able to be ſene, or not able to bee
ſene: al thei haue their creacion, and beyng by Chriſte, the onely natural ſonne of God the
father therefore of duetie, all thynges created, are bound to be obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to our ſauiour Ieſu
Chriſte, by whom we haue our creacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, our beyng, redempcion, iuſtificacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<pb facs="tcp:4757:36"/> ſanctificacion, iuſtice and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes, and all other mightes and powers,
that be good in vs, for his ſake onely, and not of our merites or deſeruynges.</p>
            <p>And he is the hed, of the body of the Churche, whiche is the beginning firſt begotten of the
ded, that he ſhould bee in all thynges the chief. For in hym it hath pleaſed the father, all
fulnes to dwel and by hym to reconſile all thynges towardes hym, and by the bloude of his
Croſſe, to pacifie al thynges, whether thei
<pb facs="tcp:4757:36"/> were in yearth, or in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: that he ſhould make peace through hymſelf.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle goeth furth, ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing vs what Chriſt is, he ſaith he is the hed of the body
of the Churche, from whence do come all goodnes to the body that is, to the whole congregacion, and
flocke of Chriſte, and that he is the ſauer, keper, and defendor, of the whole body of the
Churche, and the prouider for all neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body, and that by hym, is diſtributed
to euery parte of the body, neceſſary foode, &amp; that without hym, all membres doo periſhe,
that bee not fed by hym, and in hym, that doo not receiue health and life of hym, that bee not
preſerued &amp; keped by Chriſt
<pb facs="tcp:4757:37"/> and defended by Chriſt, the true hed of the churche. So Chriſt is the hed of the
Churche, and not the biſhoppe of Rome, as he na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth hymſelf, &amp; would be ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,
whiche thyng is high blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy to god, not to be ſuffered emo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g Chriſtians, that any
mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall man ſhould, make hymſelf equall with Chriſte, and would be called by that name, that
is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall to God. God ſaieth: I wil geue my glorie to none other. What other thyng doth the
bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Rome go about, callyng hymſelf the hed of the Churche, but to take awaie from
Chriſte, his honor and glory, and would haue it geuen to himſelf? whiche thyng god wil not
ſuffre. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let Biſhops of Rome, ceaſe from that name, and call theim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfes
<pb facs="tcp:4757:37"/> no more, hed of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, for that is Chriſte onely, as here Paule teacheth,
and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther let them beware, to call Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppes of Rome, hed of the v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſall Churche of
God, leaſt thei offende God, and diſpleaſe God, prouokyng God to poure vpon theim, his Ire
and venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce: &amp; ſmite them with eternal death, due to ſuche tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>greſſors.</p>
            <p n="2">2 He is the beginnyng, firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten of the ded.) The Greke ſaieth, he is the
beginnyng, and the firſte begotten of the ded, as you would ſay, he is beginnyng firſte
fountain and aucthor, of our life, health, reſurreccion, and ſaluacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, hauyng al goodnes in
hymſelf, and diſtributyng it to other, and therefore not without a cauſe, he is chiefeſt in
al thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,
<pb facs="tcp:4757:38"/> to him is due, the chief place in all thynges, for he is equal to the father, in
deitie, ſubſtaunce, and effecte, in power and might, and in all thynges.</p>
            <p n="3">3 For it hath pleaſed the father that all fulnes, in hym ſhould dwel.) Now he
ſheweth by what meanes, Chriſt is called the hed, of the body of the Churche, that in Chriſt
doth inhabite &amp; dwell, al fulnes of the goodnes of god the father: and by Chriſte, we
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue of Gods goodnes, as our redempcion, reconciliacion, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſinnes, iuſtice,
&amp; righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes before GOD, eternall life and felicitie, &amp; all other gif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of God, we
receiue by Chriſt onely of Gods mere mercie and grace, and not of our merites or deſeruynges,
or of our workes,
<pb facs="tcp:4757:38"/> merites, or peticions of ſainctes. Al fulnes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father, is called to dwel in
Chriſt, not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chriſt now hath receiued y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thyng, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he had not before, for all goodnes of
the father, he had before, as <hi>Ihon .v.</hi> ſaieth: As the father hath life in hymſelf,
ſo he hath geuen to the ſonne, to haue life in hymſelf, as the father raiſed ded men to
life, ſo doth the ſonne. And. <hi>Iho. xviii.</hi> Chriſt ſaid to his father, glorify me
with thy ſelfe, with the ſame glory, that I had before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world was created: but all fulnes of
the father is called, to dwell in Chriſt, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all men ſhould knowe, all the goodnes thei haue,
to come of God by Chriſte to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all that beleueth in Chriſt, ſhuld not periſhe, but
bee ſaued, and ſhould haue life euerlaſtyng by
<pb facs="tcp:4757:39"/> Chriſt with the father.</p>
            <p n="4">4 And by hym to reconſile all thynges.) He goeth forwardes, deſcribyng what benefites,
wee haue receiued by Chriſt: he ſaith that al thynges, whiche wer out of Gods fauor, to bee
reconciled again, to Gods fauor and loue: as all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whiche either for their originall ſinne, or
for their actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſynne, were out of Gods fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uor, and had offended GOD, ſhould by Chriſte
onely, bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled to Gods fauour: and haue remiſſion of their ſynnes, and be made
partakers, of euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtyng life, and that onely by Chriſte. So by Chriſt alone, all thinges
in yearth, or in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, be brought again to Gods fauor.</p>
            <p>And you whiche was farre of, and enemies in
<pb facs="tcp:4757:39"/> mynde and in euill wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, now he hath recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled you again, in the bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy of his
fleſhe, by death that he ſhould make you without fault, &amp; without all ſpottes in his
ſight.</p>
            <p>Before the Apoſtle ſhewed in parte, what Chriſte was, now he turneth his ſermon to
theſe Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſſia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and ſheweth what bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite thei haue receiued by Chriſt and that thei
ſhould loue Chriſt the better, bee more thankefull, and geue more thankes to God, for their
health, life, and ſaluaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he ſheweth what thei wer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thei receiued Chriſtes
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite: then thei were farre from life and ſaluacion, from God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lienated,
<pb facs="tcp:4757:40"/> by many vices and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, bothe originall and actuall in harte, mynde, will,
iudgement and in many euill workes, as in Idolatrie, ſuperſticion, fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, adultery,
errors and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, for lacke of knowlege, and of Goddes grace, and by their naughtie liuyng,
in the whiche thei wer brought vp in, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed, from their young age that thei committyng,
great and abhominable ſinnes, in the ſight of God, thei thought themſelfes not to ſynne,
for thei knewe not, what was ſynne, nor the daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gier of ſynne, nor yet God their creator and
maker. Suche ther be many in the worlde, brought vp in ignoraunce, and blindnes ſuperſticio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
and Idolatrie, thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth ſuperſticion and Idolatrie
<pb facs="tcp:4757:40"/> to pleaſe GOD well, the cauſe whereof, is euill bringyng vp of their parentes,
without knowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege of God, and of his will, and not taught to knowe God and his pleaſure to bee
dooen, of vs his creatures, and ſeruauntes, as we haue promiſed in our ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſme, by our
Godfathers, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſyng for vs. And here he ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth, ſome parte of their ſtates, Firſte,
that thei were farre from God, from life, healthe, and ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uacion, by reaſon of their
igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and euill bryngyng vp, in vice and ſynne, from their yong age, vnto that daie, thei
harde the worde of God preached vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And here wee maie learne not to ſticke much to
thoſe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, wherein wee haue been brought vp, from our yong age,
<pb facs="tcp:4757:41"/> whiche parauenture, haue been coumpted vertue, and worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyng of God, yet the
truth kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen, thei haue been ſuperſticion and Idolatrie, as was Pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, deckyng, giltyng
of Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, ſettyng vp of candelles be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore images: alſo again thei wer farre from GOD, and
from the houſe of Iſrael, hauyng no title to claime or chalenge any parte of life, or
ſaluacion, ye, nothyng knowyng or myndyng life, and health, to perteine to theim, that wer
Gentiles, as is more decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red at large. <hi>Ephe. ii.</hi> But theſe that were farre of,
Chriſte hath made theim partakers of life, and of heauenly ioye, bliſſe, and eternall
felicitie with God. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, thei wer enemies to God &amp; to their awne ſaluacion, bothe
<pb facs="tcp:4757:41"/> in mynde, and in euill woorkes, thei had their myndes infected and poyſoned, with
euill opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, errors and hereſies, euill and wicked iudgementes, and full of euill woorkes:
Seruyng not the liuyng GOD, true and iuſte, but many falſe Idolles, ded Images, ſtockes and
bloc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, and ofte tymes thynkyng themſelfes, to ſerue the true and liuyng GOD, when thei liued
in al ſuperſticion and Idolatry: but theſe enemies, Chriſte hath reconciled again, to the
fauor of GOD the father, in the body of his fleſh, by death, that by death of the Croſſe,
whiche he ſuffered in his humain body, for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dempcion of al, bothe Iewe and Gentile, that
will beleue in him. And thus Chriſtes death, was a
<pb facs="tcp:4757:42"/> full and ſufficient ſatiſfaccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for the ſynnes of the whole world, &amp;
for all theim, that ſhalbe ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied and ſaued. <hi>Hebre. x.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 That he ſhould make vs ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and blameles, and without ſpottes in his ſight.) Here
is ſhe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wed, for what ende and purpoſe, Chriſte reconciled vs to the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uor of the father,
that we ſhould returne again, to vice, ſynne, and to our old naughtie liuing? No no. But that
wee ſhould be holy, and liue Godly and verte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, knowe Gods will &amp; kepe it: And that we
ſhould bee faut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, that no notable faute, crime, or ſynne might be iuſtely impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, to vs
of menne, and that we ſhould ſo beare &amp; behaue our ſel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fes, in all oure affaires, that
wee might be without reprofe, &amp; that
<pb facs="tcp:4757:42"/> our faith, ſhould be ſo pure and ſtedfaſt, garniſhed with all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of
good workes, that we ded fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſynne, ſhould liue to iuſtice, as ſainct Peter ſaieth.
<hi>i. Peter .ii.</hi> Here wee maie learne, how pure &amp; holy a life, all men ſhould liue not
onely the Biſhoppe, Paſtor, and prieſte, but alſo all laie men that deſireth to bee
felowes of ſaluacion, and glory by Chriſt.</p>
            <p>If you remain in faith grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded and ſtable, and will not bee remoued fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the hope of the
Goſpell, whiche you haue harde, that was preached to all creatures vnder heauen, of the whiche, I
Paule am made a miniſter.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:4757:43"/>Nowe he ſheweth, howe thei ſhalbee blameles, without faute and ſpott, in the
ſight God, that is, if thei ſhal abide in true faith and by no affliccion, perſecuci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
proſperitie, or aduerſitie, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline or ſhrynke from true faith, but bee conſtaunt, and
ſtable in it, founded vpon Chriſt, the true foundacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and corner ſtone, cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng vnto
Chriſte, and to his doctryne. And here the Apoſtle reproueth al vnfaithfull, that be doubtfull,
inconſtaunt, and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueryng in faith, moued and toſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, hether and thether, with eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry wynde
and blaſt, and tempeſt of wether, of threatenynges of men, or hope of fauor, or pleaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res of
men. And ſpecially here is reproued, all ſuche as will be fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorers of Gods worde, as long
<pb facs="tcp:4757:43"/> as hope of fauor, pleaſure, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite or commoditie, doo come by the word of God,
and when that hope is gone, thei ſhrynke from the Goſpell, are aſhamed of it, leaue it, and
forſake it, follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng men, the world, and their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, ye, and al the knowlege, thei haue by
the Goſpell, thei turne it to a carnall libertie, and to a worldly commoditie, makyng the
Goſpell to bee as a cloke, to their coueteouſnes, pompe, plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure, inſaceable myndes, to
gette riches, landes, and poſſeſſions, and to make themſelfes riche, in worldly
poſſeſſions, and ſuche there is many nowe adaies, as Chriſt ſaieth. <hi>Math. xiii.
Multi ad tempus credunt, &amp; in tempore ten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tationis recedu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</hi> Many for a time doth beleue,
but in tyme of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptacion,
<pb facs="tcp:4757:44"/> thei ſhrynke from faith from God, but theſe be not thei, that bee blameles, and
without faute in Gods ſight, but thei bee worthy blame, and bee ſpotted with many vices and
ſynnes, &amp; ſhall not eſcape puniſhemente, excepte thei repent and amende, and be
conſtaunt in faithe. Here is two thynges required of vs, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wee ſhould be without blame or
ſpotte, in Gods ſight: the one is, that we ſhould bee conſtaunt in faithe, the ſecond,
not to ſhrinke from the hope of theſe heauenly treaſures, promiſed by the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell,
preached to all creatures vnder heauen. See the mightie power of GOD, that made his worde to bee
preached through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all the worlde, in the ſpite of all enemies to the Goſpell, and
<pb facs="tcp:4757:44"/> magre to their tethe, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Apoſtle was not aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, to call
hymſelf, not a lorde, but a Miniſter of the Goſpell, called of God. And here he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proueth,
thoſe biſhoppes or hye prelates, that will be called lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, and yet thei be no miniſters of
the Goſpell of Chriſte: ſeldom or neuer preached Chriſtes Goſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pell.</p>
            <p>Now I ioy in my ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferynges for you, and ful<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fill that whiche are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hynde, of the
affliccions of Chriſt in my fleſhe, for his body ſake, whiche is the Churche, of the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che
Churche, I am made a Miniſter, accordyng to
<pb facs="tcp:4757:45"/> the ordinaunce of GOD whiche is geuen to me e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monges you, to fulfil the worde of God:
A miſtery hid from the worlde, and from generacions, but now ſhewed ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly to his ſainctes,
to whom God would make it knowen.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle, becauſe he ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed before, that the Goſpel was preached, throughout al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
world and that he was a miniſter of it, by the ordinaunce of God: now he ſheweth that he
ſuffered ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny affliccions for it, and for the health of them, to whom he prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ched it, and that
he was not ſory for his affliccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, but rather did reioyſe in theim, for the Goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les
<pb facs="tcp:4757:45"/> ſake, and for the health of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſaiyng: now I reioyſe in my ſufferyng,
and ſuffre mine afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions gladly, for the Goſpelles ſake, and for you Coloſſia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and
other of the Gentiles, knowyng by that meanes, God woorketh your ſaluacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And in theſe
wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des Paule maketh anſwere, to carnall men, that would obiecte to hym after this maner. If this
doctryne that thou preacheſt be true, and come of God fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, of the whiche commeth life,
and eternall felicitie, as thou ſaieſt, how can it bee that theſe, that be preachers &amp;
ſetters furth of it, bee moſte miſerable of all men, leaſte eſtemed or regarded, caſt
in fetters and in priſon, bee called heretiques, lollers, decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of the people, ſedicious
me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:4757:46"/> and ſuffre ſome times, ſhameful death for his doctryne ſake? To theſe
carnall men, ſaincte Paule maketh here anſwere, ſaiyng: that he ſuffereth ſlaunder,
chec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes and rebukes, impriſonment and fetters, not for his ſinnes or euill dooynges, but for
the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelles ſake, and for their ſakes, to whom it was preached, which came to healthe, by
the Goſpell preached, and therefore it was no ſhame to ſuffre for the Goſpell, but rather
commendable, &amp; that theſe affliccions was not hurte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ſuffered
vniuſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that afflicted other thei were dampnable: and that God ſuffered euill
men, ſo to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict the good, that the iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to the euill, ſhould bee the more greater, and
that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:4757:46"/> by muche tribulacions, enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ioy &amp; bliſſe, after the example of
Chriſt, &amp; that the euill ſhould be confounded, ſeyng thei could by no affliccions, hynder
or lette the word of God to be preached, or to hynder it or lette it, that it ſhould ſprede
abrode &amp; increaſe: for the more the euil goth about by affliccions, perſecucion or death,
to ſtop the worde of God, the more it goeth forwardes, by that meanes, God will not haue his
woorde, altogether ſtopped and hid, and oft tymes it chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth, that by euil men, the worde of
God is promoted and ſetfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes by that meanes, by the whiche euill men, went about to hynder
it: example in Chriſtes death, and in the death of many other, for Chriſtes Goſpel
ſake.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb facs="tcp:4757:47"/>2 I fulfill that whiche are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind, of the affliccions of Chriſt in my fleſhe,
for his body ſake.) This place hath of ſome euill men, been wreſted oute of tune, and from
his true ſence, to the greate contumely of Chriſtes bloud, as thei would ſaie: that
Chriſtes bloud was not a full ſatiſfaccion, for our rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pcio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geuenes of our ſynnes,
but that to it ſome thyng lacked, whiche by our woorke, deede, merite, or affliccions, ſhould
bee fulfilled and ſatiſfied, as thei ſhould ſaie that Chriſtes paſſion was not
ſufficient, to take awaie the ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the whole worlde, and as Chriſte had not fully
ſatiſfied, for the ſinnes of all men, whiche thyng to thinke or ſaie, is greate
blaſphemie to Chriſt, and to his
<pb facs="tcp:4757:47"/> holy bloud: God forbid that any any man, ſhould thinke ſo or ſay it. For
Chriſt by his death, once for all, hath fully and perfitely ſatiſfied, for the ſynnes of al
me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and by one oblacion, made them perfite that ſhalbe holy. <hi>Hebr. x.</hi> He entred once
into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy place called <hi>ſancta ſanctorum,</hi> &amp; found eternall redempcion.
<hi>Hebre. iiii.</hi> Wherfore this is an vndoubted truthe, euer to bee beleued of all
chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſte by his paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and death, hath taken awaie, all the ſynnes of the
worlde, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out our workes, deedes, or meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, for he nedeth not our woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, merites, or
affliccions, to purge man fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſynne, as ſaincte Ihon ſaith. <hi>i. Ihon .i.</hi> The bloud
of Chriſte hath purged vs, from all our ſynnes: and Ihon in the
<pb facs="tcp:4757:48"/> Reuelacion: he hath waſſhed vs from oure ſynnes, in his bloud. Of theſe
ſcriptures it is certain, that thei bee iniurious to the bloude of Chriſte, and blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers
of Chriſt, that thynke our workes or affliccions, to purge vs from our ſynnes, or to
ſatiſfy for ſynnes, for theſe bee offices, onely perteinyng to Chriſte a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone: And for
our affliccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, thei bee not worthie the glory, that ſhall bee ſhewed to the electe of God.
<hi>Roma. viii.</hi> What blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie canne bee more to Chriſtes bloude, then to thinke that
oure litle nothyng, can make perfite, that Chriſt left vnperfite, or can ſatiſfy or fulfil,
that Chriſt hath not fulfilled, and fully ſatiſfied, without our woorkes, merites, dedes, or
ſatiſfaccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? What can
<pb facs="tcp:4757:48"/> we doo, that could pacifie Gods Ire and diſpleaſure, or deſerue life
euerlaſtyng? ſurely nothing. And where as Paule ſaith here, I fulfil that are behynd, or that
dooth remain, of the affliccions of Chriſte, is nothyng els, but that ſainct Peter ſaith
<hi>i. Peter .ii.</hi> where he ſaith, that Chriſt hath ſuffered for vs, leauyng to vs
e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xample, that we ſhould followe his footſteppes: that is, that we ſhould ſuffre
affliccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, after the example of Chriſt, and the afflic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cions that we ſuffre, Chriſt ſaith
that he ſuffereth theim, becauſe we be membres of his body, and Chriſt ſuffereth when his
mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers ſuffereth. <hi>Actes .ix.</hi> GOD ſpake to Paule. <hi>Saule, Saule, quid me
perſequeris?</hi> Why doeſt thou perſecute me? And ſo Chriſte is
<pb facs="tcp:4757:49"/> called to ſuffre twoo waies: one way in his awne naturall body, as when he
ſuffered vpon the croſſe: another way, when he ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth in his miſticall membres, in
the bodies of his elect people After the firſte waie, nothyng was left vnperfite, as touchyng the
me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bres that remaineth, that Chriſte in theim ſhould ſuffre, vnto the worldes ende, and that
thei by pacient ſuffryng, ſhould entre into the kyngdom of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and ſo ſainct Paule here
mea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned, ſaiyng: I fulfill that which is behind, of the paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Chriſt that is:
Chriſte did ſuffre, bothe to take awaie oure ſynnes, and alſo for our example, to ſuffre,
ſo I do nowe, ſuffre affliccions for the Goſpels ſake, to geue other example, to ſuffre
paciently ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:4757:49"/> affliccions, as ſhal chaunce vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to theim, here in this worlde, for the truthe
ſake, and for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte of other, as he teſtifieth of hymſelf. <hi>i. Corin. i.</hi>
Saiyng, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we are puniſhed, or that we ſuffre, it is for your comfort and health. So
Paule ſuffered af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliccions, for the example of the whole Churche of God: that all ſhould
learne of Paule, to ſuffre paciently for Chriſtes ſake, for his worde, and for his Goſpell.
And ſo this is behynde of the Paſſion of Chriſte, not that any thyng remayned vnperfite, in
Chriſtes paſſion, whiche by our ſuffrynges, ſhould be made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite: But that as
Chriſte in his awne body here ſuffered, hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, cold, thurſt, many affliccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and death,
ſo he doth dow ſuffre
<pb facs="tcp:4757:50"/> in his members, and that thyng the Paſſion of Chriſte ſheweth, that we
ſhould ſo do, ſuffre with Chriſt, and ariſe with hym. So as parteinyng to our redempcio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
iuſtificacion, and ſaluacion, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng remaineth, that was not fulfilled, in the paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of
Chriſt, but as touchyng the ſufferyng of Chriſte in his membres, this remaineth to be
fulfilled, in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of theim: as ſainct Paule ſaieth. <hi>Omnes qui uolunt pie ui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere, in
Chriſto Ieſu, perſecutio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem patientur.</hi> All that will liue godly in Chriſt, muſt
ſuffre per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecucion and affliccions, here in this worlde.</p>
            <p n="3">3 A miſterie hid from the world and from generacions, but now ſhewed ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly to his
ſainctes, to whom God would haue it kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen.)
<pb facs="tcp:4757:50"/> Paul ſaied, he was made, not of man, but of God, and by the ordinaunce of God, a
mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Goſpell, whiche Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell was hid from the Gentiles, and from a greate parte
of the world, of a long tyme: From the beginnyng of the worlde, vnto Chriſtes tyme, a fewe of the
Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles excepted, to whom it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed God, of his eſpecial grace, to ſhewe his Goſpell,
his will and pleaſure, and ſo did geue to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> faith alſo, by the whiche thei wer ſaued.
For what cauſes, GOD would not haue had his worde, openly preached to the Gentiles vnto
Chriſtes tyme, it is not of vs to bee curiouſly ſearched, nor inquired, it is enough for vs,
to knowe that, that was his will, &amp; for his glory, as holy ſcripture
<pb facs="tcp:4757:51"/> telleth vs, whether it was that thei had by their ſynnes deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, their
blyndnes and da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion (as thei had in very deede) or it was that God knewe, the hardnes of their
hartes, &amp; their ſtiffeneckes, and that thei would not haue receiued it, before Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtes
comming, if the Goſpel had been preached vnto them, or that God reſerued that miſterie, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
the commyng of our ſauioure Chriſt, that by hym all goodnes ſhould be knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to come to vs
by Chriſt, and in Chriſt, and all miſteries, by Chriſte to bee ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and ſhewed, to
oure profite and commoditie, and that onely of the goodnes of GOD, of his mere mercie and grace,
and not of our workes, merites, or deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynges. And here we maie lerne
<pb facs="tcp:4757:51"/> two thynges, the one is: that the miſterie of the Goſpell, to bee o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly
ſhewed emonges the Gen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiles, was hid from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng, and was not openly prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, to theim
in Paules tyme: Therfore tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes is to be geuen to GOD, of whoſe grace it was ſhewed ſo now
in our daies, that the veritie of Gods holy worde, is plainly opened to vs, more then it was in our
fathers daies the cauſe is not of manne, but of Gods goodnes to vs, not of our wiſedom,
pollicy, connyng, lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng, goodnes, but onely of Gods grace, and becauſe it hath ſo pleaſed
hym, to ſhewe to vs that truthe, that was hid from ourfathers, that we ſhould more thanke, and
glorifie God for the ſame, and vſe the light of Gods
<pb facs="tcp:4757:52"/> truthe ſhewed to vs better, and liue accordyng to the Goſpell, opened to vs now
in our daies. Another thyng wee maye here learne, that GOD ſheweth his truthe, and openeth the
light of his Goſpell, &amp; of miſteries long hid, when it pleaſeth him, and to whom it
pleaſeth hym, and not at the will or pleaſure of manne, that none ſhould thynke, he may
vnderſtand the holy ſcriptures, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yt pleaſeth himſelf, or of his awne might or power.
Learne y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the knowleg of holy ſcriptures, and of miſteries hid, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth of God onely, &amp;
not of man, God v<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſynge our dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; labors, as meanes by y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which, God vſeth to geue
his giftes, of ſciences &amp; knowlege of holy ſcriptures.</p>
            <p>whiche as the riches
<pb facs="tcp:4757:52"/> of the glorie of this mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie, emonges the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, whiche is Chriſt in you,
the hope of glorye whom wee ſhewe, moni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyng euery manne, and teachyng all men, in all
wiſedom, that we ſhould make euery man perfite in Chriſte Ieſu, for the whiche thyng, I
labour with all force, after the might of hym, workyng in me by ſtrength.</p>
            <p>Now y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtle ſheweth what was that miſterie, that was hid from the worlde, that it was
the riches, of the glory of Chriſte, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiles, that is Chriſt
<pb facs="tcp:4757:53"/> in you, that is: that the Gentiles receiued Chriſte by faithe, and ſaluacion by
Chriſte, was vnto the Gentiles, ſuche riches &amp; glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, as paſſed all other riches and
glory, that no toungue could tel it, nor harte thynke it: that was Chriſt to bee with theim, and
all benefites of Chriſte, to come to the Gentiles, by true faithe in Chriſte, whiche is the
hope of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall glory.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The hope of glory.) He ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth that Chriſte is our hope of glory, and none els,
neither his mother, Ihon, ne Iames: &amp; here is declared, the effecte of ſainct Paules
doctryne, that it was, that all menne ſhould put their hope and truſt of glory to come, in no
other, but in Chriſte Ieſu, not in circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciſion, in no ſacrifice,
<pb facs="tcp:4757:53"/> ceremony, or worke of the lawe, in no deedes of men, not in meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of ſainctes
departed, not in maſſes of <hi>Scala caeli,</hi> but in Chriſt alone our ſauior.</p>
            <p n="3">3 That wee ſhould make euery manne perfite in Chriſte Ieſu.) Loke to what ende
ſainct Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les doctrine doth extende, that it was to make euery manne (as muche as in hym lied)
perfite in Chriſte Ieſu, &amp; that thei ſhould lacke nothyng, that perteined to eternall
life and felicitie, &amp; that thyng to be doen, by the woorde of GOD, that he preached and
taughte. This place maketh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all them, that would kepe men ſtill, in their infirmitie
and weakenes, and would haue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alwaies weakelynges, and not perfite men, ye, not to increaſe
to
<pb facs="tcp:4757:54"/> perfite men, but to bee children waueryng with euery blaſte of doctryne, nowe ready
to receiue this doctryne, now that, and not able to iudge themſelfes, in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt truthes,
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctryne of ſaincte Ihon: biddyng vs to proue the ſpirites, whether thei be of
God or no?</p>
            <p n="4">4 For the whiche I labor with al might.) The Apoſtle labored with all his power and
dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, to bryng al men, to perfeccion in Chriſt, &amp; to a full perfite know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege of
Chriſte, and of his bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites, that al men ſhould knowe perfitely their health, life, &amp;
ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uacion, to come to theim, onely by Chriſt, and that there was no health, without Chriſt.
And this he did, by the mightie power of God, workyng in hym, or by the
<pb facs="tcp:4757:54"/> miniſtracion, of that woorkyng Godly woorde, whiche he prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched: for God by his
worde, pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely and ſincerely preached doth worke: therefore it is called a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uely woorde, for it
geueth life. And here wee maie learne, that the doctryne of ſaincte Paule, and of other that
wrote the holy ſcriptures, not to bee of man (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though thei that wrote or prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched them wer
men) but of God, and of his holy ſpirite, by whoſe inſpiracion thei wrote, as Peter ſaieth.
<hi>ii. Peter .i.</hi> Learne to attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to God, all thynges that be dooen well of vs, and not
to our ſelfes, as Paule did here to God workyng in hym, and by hym.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The .ii. Chapiter.</head>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:4757:55"/>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>OR I woulde you knew what care I had for you, and for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that are of Laodice, and
as many as hath not ſen my perſone in the fleſhe, that their hartes mighte take co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort,
ſeyng thei be ioyned in charitie, &amp; in al riches of certain perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of
vnderſtanding in to the knowlege of the miſterie of God, and the father, and of Chriſte, in
who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are hid all the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, of the wiſedo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and knowlege of God.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:4757:55"/>The Apoſtle here getteth the fauor, of theſe Coloſſians, and of the
Laodicenſes, ſhewyng his hartes deſire, was to confort the hartes of them, that had not
ſene hym corporally, by the ſpirite of God, and that thei ſhould agre, and cleaue together as
me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bres in the body ſurely, by a true faith knowyng that all treaſures of wiſedom, and
knowlege of God are laied vp in Chriſte, whom if thei ſhould haue, thei ſhould lacke nothyng,
who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> if thei lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, thei ſhould haue nothyng, whatſoeuer they had wythout Chriſt. This
place teacheth one of vs, to be carefull for another, that we might haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy
ghoſt, and by Gods worde as Paule was for theſe Coloſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and Laodicenſes: and it
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proueth
<pb facs="tcp:4757:56"/> all theim that care not for other, whether thei flete or ſinke, whether thei haue
know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lege of Gods worde or no, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thei bee ſaued or dampned. Ye, this place reproueth al
them that bee haters of Gods worde, that care not for it, but conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pne and deſpiſe it, that
bee contenci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and vncharitable, caryng not what chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to other, ſo thei be well
theimſelfes, liue in welth and pleaſure. Learne, it is the office of a true paſtor, to
edifie, not to deſtroye, to feede, not to bryng to deathe, to conforte mennes hartes in
Chriſte, not to diſcomfort and diſcorage theim, from Chriſte, or from his holy worde and
Goſpell.</p>
            <p n="2">2 When thei ſhalbee ioyned in Charitie.) In theſe woordes is
<pb facs="tcp:4757:56"/> ſhewed, how their hartes ſhalbe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forted: that is, when thei ſhall be
compacted and knit together, ſo in charitie, that one of theim, cannot bee ſeperated from
ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that thei be as ſure one, cou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pled to another, as membres in the body, bee ioyned
together, &amp; that thei all thynke and ſaie one thyng, and that alſo, when thei bee ioyned
together, with a true faithe, whiche he calleth here ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, of the ſure perſwaſion in the
knowlege of the miſterye of GOD. And here me thynketh ſaincte Paule, declareth what faithe is,
that it is riches of ſure perſwaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in knowlege of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des woorde, and that knowlege to bee
ſo ſure, that it cannot bee falſe, or brought in doubte, for faith knoweth the truth of
god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des
<pb facs="tcp:4757:57"/> woorde and promiſes, to the whiche it ſtaieth ſurely, and will not be moued
from it. And here he ſheweth, that thoſe men, that bee doubtfull in their doctryne,
inconſtaunt, or waueryng, haue not faythe. For true faythe, commeth of ſure knowlege of Gods
worde, and hath annexed to hym, hope, and charitie, and obedience, to do Gods co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dementes, al
reſpectes of world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly riches, fauor or pleaſure, well or wo, ſet a parte, example in
A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Iſaac, Iacob, and other holy fathers.</p>
            <p n="3">3 In Chriſt bee all treaſures of wiſedome and knowlege, laied vp in ſcore.) As he
would ſay, he that hath Chriſt, he hath al thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges, neceſſary for his ſaluacion, as all
wiſedome, knowlege, ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue,
<pb facs="tcp:4757:57"/> holines, health, and life, he wanteth nothyng, he hath a well of all goodnes, euer
ſpryngyng and flowyng ouer, he hath trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, that ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be ſpent or wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted. Here the
Apoſtle reproueth arrogant men, and proude Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophiers, that thynketh hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main learnyng, and
knowlege of mannes learnyng, to bee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred, aboue the learnyng of Chriſte. Ye, here he
checketh all theim, that bee more ſtudious of humain ſciences, then thei bee of Gods holy
diuinitie. Ye, all thei be reproued, that will ſpend, da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yes, nightes, &amp; yeres, in the
ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of humain Philoſophie, and will not geue more ſtudie, to the knowlege of Gods holy
worde, by the whiche, Chriſte is gotten by faithe, and keped by faithe.
<pb facs="tcp:4757:58"/> and he that hath Chriſt, hath all thinges, &amp; he that lacketh Chriſt hath
nothyng, haue he neuer ſo muche humaine learnyng, Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophie, or Poetrie: as Tully and
Demoſtenes, was found in thende, as thei had had, no lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng, becauſe thei lacked Chriſt
and Godly doctryne, for al lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng, muſte geue place to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes doctryne, as moſte chief,
far excellyng all other learnynges.</p>
            <p>This I ſaie, that none ſhould deceiue you with entiſyng woordes, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I am abſent
fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you in the fleſh, yet in the ſpirit, I am preſent with you, ioyyng &amp; ſeyng your
ordre and ſtedfaſtnes of
<pb facs="tcp:4757:58"/> your faithe in Chriſte.</p>
            <p>Now he ſheweth for what end he ſaid all treaſures of wiſedom and knowlege of God, to be
hid in Chriſte, that it was, that thei ſhould not ſuffre theimſelfes to be deceiued, by no
intiſyng wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of Rethorique, or of mannes lernyng, or by no other doctrine had it neuer ſo
greate pretenſe of holines, or apparaunce of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and by it to be brought to the degrees
of humain Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy, from the pure &amp; clere ſpring and fountain, of liuely water of the
word of God. And he exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to abide and ſticke ſure, to that faithe thei had
receiued, by Gods woorde, and that in no wiſe, thei ſhould turne from it, to Iewiſhnes, or to
the lawe, to the ſacrifices, or Ceremonies of the
<pb facs="tcp:4757:59"/> lawe, as to thinke thei cannot be ſaued without theim: when by Chriſt, thei haue
all thynges ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie for ſaluacion: nor yet it is not neceſſary, to ioyne with
Chriſt any other thyng, as lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng of Philoſophie, workes of the lawe, Ceremonies,
Tradici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of men, as without them, no man can be ſaued: For Chriſt is a ſufficient
ſauior, without all theſe thynges: nor it is not nede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to ſaluacion, to ioyne any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
thyng with Chriſte, as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for ſaluacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, without the which, ſaluacion cannot be
had. This place doth reproue theim, that ſaith, menne cannot vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de holy ſcripture
truly, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out humain Philoſophie, and therefore, thei ſay, that Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie is
neceſſarie, and that yong
<pb facs="tcp:4757:59"/> men, brought vp in the Vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities, muſt nedes learne Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophie: thei will
not ſuffre theim to ſtudie diuinitie, before thei haue ſpente, three or foure yeres in
Philoſophy, in Ariſtotle, or in Platoes woorkes: that by Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophie, thei maie bee hable to
iudge of diuinitie, and ſo it ofte tymes commeth to paſſe, that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinitie is iudged by
Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie, and as the Heathen Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophier, hath thought and iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of diuinitie: ſo
many young mennes iudgementes be, and ſo the ſtudious youth in Vniuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, bee poyſoned
by humain Philoſophie, in their firſte ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies: for as it is ofte tymes ſene, that the
veſſell will kepe lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the ſmell of that liquor, that was firſte putte in it: ſo the
ſtudious
<pb facs="tcp:4757:60"/> youth, firſt brought vp in Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile learnyng, kepe long the Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles iudgementes
and maners: of theſe Gentile aucthors, thei haue red in their youth, and it is a greate grace, if
euer thei bee brought from theim, and that is a greate cauſe, why ſo many brought vp in Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tile
aucthors, haue more ſwetenes and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, in Gentile learning, then in the learnyng of
Chriſte, and of Goddes worde, whiche thei con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempne and deſpiſe, for Gentile learnyng.
Therefore I thinke it moſte expedient, for Gods glory to be ſprede abrode, &amp; for the
ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of many, and for true iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement to be had, that all youth ſhould bee verteouſly
broughte vp, after the knowlege of Gods word, that thei might haue their
<pb facs="tcp:4757:60"/> iudgementes, truly formed and directed, after the knowlege of holy ſcripture, &amp;
that thei ſhould be taught, by ſobre, diſcrete, and learned men, the true ſcience of
ſcripture, and howe thei ſhould take it, and come to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege of it, with what humblenes
and mekenes, oft times, geuyng themſelfes too faithful praier, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiryng the knowlege of holy
ſcri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ptures of GOD, to the glory of GOD, to their ſaluacion, and to the commoditie of
other.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Although I am abſente in fleſhe, yet I am preſent with you in the ſpirite.) Note
what affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion Paule had, to theſe Coloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians, he was preſent with them in ſpirite,
although he was ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in his body from theim, he exhorted the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to continue in faith
<pb facs="tcp:4757:61"/> hope, and in Charitie, and not to ſhrynke from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, one here brede ſo he
ſtudied to profite them, and to teache them the way to ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion: and that is, to bee
preſent with them in ſpirite.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Ioiyng and ſeyng your ordre and ſurenes of your faithe in Chriſte.) He commendeth
theim for twoo thinges, and was glad to ſe in them ſtedfaſtnes: the one was, that he
reioyſed to ſee the good &amp; ſemely ordre, vſed emon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges theim: a good ordre in doo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng
of thynges, emonges Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, is to be commended, and where is no ordre, there is
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion: ſainct Paule. <hi>i. Cori. xiiii.</hi> Would all thynges ſhould bee dooen, after
a ſemely ordre, and after a decent faſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and here he commendeth a good ordre, and
<pb facs="tcp:4757:61"/> reproueth thoſe, that kepe no or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre nor comelines. He commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth theim alſo,
for their ſurenes of their faithe in Chriſt, that by no craft, or intiſyng perſwaſion
thei ſhrynked from Chriſt, or fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> true beleue in Chriſte. He repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth here, inconſtaunt
men, and ſuche as will bee moued, with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery blaſt or doctryne. He com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, not that
thei ſhould bee proude, but that thei ſhould more and more, go forwardes in vertue, for vertue
commended, increaſeth muche more.</p>
            <p>As you haue receiued Chriſt Ieſus our Lorde, ſo walke in him, that you maie bee rooted in
hym, and buylded in hym, and made ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g by faith, and
<pb facs="tcp:4757:62"/> as you haue learned, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundyng in hym, with geuyng of thankes.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle exhorteth theim to go forwardes, and increaſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery daie more &amp; more, in
know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege, in faithe, in hope, in chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, as thei haue receiued Chriſt, and faithe in hym, and
all trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of perfeccion and ſaluacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be had in Chriſt, by the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the
Goſpel: ſo he would haue them, increaſe in knowlege and in all vertue, euery daye more and
more, and not to ceaſſe from wel doyng, &amp; good workes appoynted of God to be doen.</p>
            <p n="2">2 So that you might be rooted in hym, and buylded and made ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g by faith.) The
Apoſtle re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth conſtancie, and ſurenes
<pb facs="tcp:4757:62"/> in them, that thei ſhould not bee moueable, with euery wynde of doctryne, but that
thei ſhould haue ſure faithe, conſtaunt hope and bee perfite in charitie, in the knowlege of
God, and of Chriſt and as a tre, ſurely rooted in the ground, cannot well be plucked vp, ſo
ſure he would haue theim rooted in faithe, and that thei ſhould buylde vpon Chriſte, the
ſure foundacion, and not vpon menne, mennes phantaſies and dreames, tradicions, religions of
menne, or vpon mennes good intentes, without Gods worde. Chriſte is the true foundacion, that
will not bee moued, by no winde nor wether. <hi>i. Cor. iii.</hi> Vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſte we ſhould buylde
ſuche workes, as bee mete for Chriſte the foundacion: and thei bee the
<pb facs="tcp:4757:63"/> woorkes, commaunded in holy ſcripture, by gold, ſiluer, and pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cious ſtones,
ſignified. <hi>i. Cor. iii.</hi> And not voluntary woorkes, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnified by woode, haye,
ſtobble, whiche tried by the fire, will not ſtande, but either ſmodder as haye, or els burne
as woode and ſtobble: but yet thei that hath doen theſe workes, ſhalbe ſaued if thei repent
and ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, and cal to GOD, for mercie and grace, and do the workes of the ſpirit.</p>
            <p n="3">3 As you haue been taught a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundyng in knowlege, with ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng of thankes.) He moueth men
to increaſe in knowlege of Chriſte, and in true faithe, and Charitie, and in theſe to excell,
but alwaie with geuyng than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes to God, whiche hath geuen the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> power, to do good, that none
<pb facs="tcp:4757:63"/> ſhould aſcribe the good workes he dooeth to hym, to his mighte and power, but to
God the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cthor of all goodnes. <hi>Iames .i.</hi> Learne that it is not enough, to haue knowlege
of Chriſt, and of his benefites, but all men muſte increaſe, in the knowlege of god whiche
knowlege commeth by Gods worde. This place repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that loueth not to rede the holy
ſcriptures, that wil not ſuffre theim to bee red, ye, ſcarſe will ſuffre the Bible, to
bee in their Pariſhe Churches, muche leſſe in their houſes.</p>
            <p>Take hede that no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deceiue you by Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy, and vain deceipt, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the tradicions of
men after the eleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of the
<pb facs="tcp:4757:64"/> world, &amp; not after Chriſt. For in hym doth dwel al fulnes of the godhed
cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porally, and you are in hym fulfilled, whiche is the hed of rule &amp; power.</p>
            <p>Now Paule ſheweth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> what thei ſhould eſcheue and flee, that thei ſhould eſcheue all
pſudoa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, &amp; falſe deceiuers, which by ſubtile crafte, went aboute to deceiue
theim, and to plucke the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from Chriſt, and from true faith in Chriſt, to errors hereſies,
euil and pernicious doctryne, &amp; that by probable reaſons, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions, taken of
mannes do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrynes, of the wiſedome of the fleſhe, of tradicions of menne, of Ceremonies, and of
other vain,
<pb facs="tcp:4757:64"/> thynges, ſo wee knowe, it is the office of a good paſtor, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to teache
good thynges, and to exhorte to the ſame, with all perſwaſions, but alſo to moniſh men,
to be ware of euill thynges as of euill doctors, and euill do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. As firſt, he willeth to
take hede, that no man catche theim, as their praye, and ſteale vpon them, as vnwarned of falſe
&amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiptfull iugglers, that by craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and ſubtile meanes, go about to deceiue theim, and
by carnall wiſedome bryngeth theim, from the truth to falſhed, form veritie to fables and lies,
errors, here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, euill opinions, and corru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pte iudgementes, and ſo plucke you from Chriſte,
to the deuill, from light to darknes, from life to death. And here the Apoſtle
<pb facs="tcp:4757:65"/> alludeth to ſuche, as lye priuely in watche, to take and ſnare o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnwares,
and ſo thei take theim and cary them awaie, and make theim, their praye and bonde men or
priſoners: euen ſo do theſe falſe teachers, ſeducers of other, deceiue the ſymple, by
faire flatteryng wordes, preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng greate holines, but (the truth knowen) they teach no ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines
at all, but muche Idolatry and ſuperſticion, falſe truſt, and vain hope, lies for truthe,
and death for life, ſekyng health and ſaluacion, where none is to bee founde: ſuche were
thei, that did not aſcribe to Chriſte, fully our whole iuſtificacion, ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion,
rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pcion, remiſſion of ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and life euerlaſtyng: that made men to runne, hether and
<pb facs="tcp:4757:65"/> thether, to ſeke ſauiours, rede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, and helpers, &amp; not to God alone, and
ſuche be all thei, that ſeke to come to the father of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, by another waie, then by
Chriſte alone.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Lette no man deceiue you by Philoſophie, &amp; vain deceiuyng, after conſtitucions
of men, after the elementes of the worlde, and not after Chriſte.) Now he ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth foure
thynges ſpecially, by the whiche, pſeudoapoſtles, falſe preachers deceiued theim. The
firſte he ſaieth, it was by Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophie, of the Heathen Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiers, inuented and
excogita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by manne, contrary to Gods Lawe and will, meaſuryng all thynges, by naturall
reaſon, and worldy witte, and that to bee of no truthe, that naturall reaſon,
<pb facs="tcp:4757:66"/> could not attein vnto. And here he dooth not reiecte, all Gentile Philoſophie, for
there is many thynges in Gentile philoſophie, that bee not repugnaunt to holy ſcriptures, but
agre very well to it, and thoſe doctrines, are not to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tempned: but that doctryne is to be
refuſed and contempned that is contrary to holy ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, that plucketh me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt,
and from the ſtudie of holy ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, and from the true iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of holy ſcriptures. The
A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle would wee ſhould, forme our iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, after holy ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, and our maners to
fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe holy ſcripture, and not that we ſhould iudge, after the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Philoſophiers, &amp;
haue ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners like to the Heathen, but he would haue vs rectifie our iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gementes,
<pb facs="tcp:4757:66"/> after Chriſte and his doctryne, &amp; to gather good ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, in al veritie and
truthe, iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and righteouſnes, of the veritie it ſelf, and not of that do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctryne, where
as falſed is. And therefore I thynke thei do euill, and not after the counſaill of ſainct
Paule, whiche thei theim ſelfes do, and willeth other to do ſo, &amp; ſpecially ſtudious
youthe: firſt to rede and ſtudie, humain Philoſophie, &amp; by ſtatutes byn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth all youth,
to ſtudie three or foure yeres Philoſophie, &amp; then after, to geue their ſtudy to
diui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nitie: but this is a prepoſterous order in ſtudy, and doeth muche hurte, to many young men
ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious, and peruerteth their iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gementes and maners, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth Heathen and Gentile ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,

<pb facs="tcp:4757:67"/> to bee ſo graffed in youth, that ſcarſe thei can bee plucked our again, and
ſome will neuer forget their Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tile maners, thei haue learned of the Gentile phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy, in
their youth: and ſome be ſo geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to the loue of Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophie, that for it, thei conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pne
diuinitie, and thynke the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege of Gods holy woorde, but a rude knowlege, and nothyng ſo
greate learnyng, as is the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng of Philoſophie, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, thei forſake all other
lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng, &amp; ſticketh ſtill to Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie, and in it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſumeth all their life: as
ſome be drouned in Tul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſome in Plato, ſome in Sene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca, ſome in one Philoſophiers
doctryne, &amp; ſome in another, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no learnyng ſauoreth in his mouth but that ſmelleth of
this, or that
<pb facs="tcp:4757:67"/> philoſophier, in whoſe learnyng he hath been brought vp, in ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of it, and
will ſcarſe by pluc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, from the ſauor of his wyne, put firſt in newe and young
bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telles: and this is the cauſe of muche inpietie, error and hereſie corrupt iudgement,
ignoraunce and blyndnes, in the knowlege of Gods worde. For if the ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous youthe of the
Vniuerſities, were as diligently, vnder ſober, ſad, diſcrete, and learned menne, brought vp
in the earneſt ſtudie of Gods holy woorde, as thei be in Ariſtotiles, Plato, and Cice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ros
woorkes, there ſhould bee muche more Godly learnyng, better iudgementes, and better maners, and
muche more better liuyng, then there is. What is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſe of errors, but ignoraunce
<pb facs="tcp:4757:68"/> of ſcripture, as Chriſt ſaid to the Sadduces. <hi>Math. xxii.</hi> Ye erre, not
knowyng the ſcriptures, ſo do many erre, becauſe thei know not the holy ſcriptures, and the
truthe of Goddes will, and the cauſe is thei bee brought vp fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their youth, not in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true
know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege of Gods woorde, will, and pleaſure. Therefore me thynke, that hye Maieſtrates and
Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> perteineth, as wel to procure the health of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule, as of the body, of their
obedient ſubiectes, not onely that they ſhould bee learned, in holy ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, to beare
good affeccion and mynde, to holy ſcriptures, and to ſee theſe thynges to bee doen, bothe in
themſelfes, and in their ſubiectes, that holy ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture willeth euery man, to doo
<pb facs="tcp:4757:68"/> in his vocacion, but alſo that their ſubictes ſhould haue, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient
knowlege in holy ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res, that thei might iudge righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely, and liue Godly, and that at no
tyme, thei ſhould declyne from Goddes woorde and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement, whiche euery man muſte kepe,
that ſhalbee ſaued, and come to ſaluacion and life by Chriſt. The ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, to beware thei
be not deceiued, and that is vain decepcion, what learnyng ſo euer it be, that deceiueth men, and
bryngeth them fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the truth of Chriſte, and from the veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Gods worde: that doctrine is
called vain deceipt, for it brin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geth into errors, hereſies, falſe doctryne, whether it be
Logique Philoſophie, Rethorique, or any other wiſedom of the fleſhe, or of
<pb facs="tcp:4757:69"/> the world, that hath appearaunce of truthe, or of holines, and doo not bryng truthe
with it. This place reproueth all errors, here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, lies, falſed, and all ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
doctryne, that prouoketh men alwaie, from Chriſtes do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctryne, and from the truthe of Gods woorde.
The third thyng to bee ware of, that by it thei bee not deceiued: is the tradicions of men, by the
whiche, pſeudoa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles went aboute to deceiue men: ſaiyng, tradicions of men, are either to
be preferred aboue Gods word &amp; commaundemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, or at the leaſt, equall with theim. Ye, thei
would haue men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes lawes and decrees, kepte and obſerued, aboue Gods la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes, and for the
obſeruacion of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes lawes, thei breake God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des
<pb facs="tcp:4757:69"/> commaundementes, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſte threatneth woo euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyng. <hi>Math. xv.</hi>
Saiyng: woo be to you Hypocrytes, that haue broken Gods commaundemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, for your tradicions.
Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, thei taught tradicions, as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to ſaluacion, &amp; that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the kepyng
of theim, thei could not bee ſaued. Thirdly, thei thought it dedly ſynne, to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit mannes
tradicions and Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, and as like offence to breake mannes tradicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, as to breake Gods
commaundemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. Fourthly, thei thought tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicions of men, to purge menne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſinne, ye, to
ſatiſfie for ſinnes and to bee full ſatiſfaccions for ſynnes. Fiftly, thei compted
tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and ordinaunces of men, to be holines, to make men holy
<pb facs="tcp:4757:70"/> and good, to take awaie ſynne, to deſerue the grace of GOD, to bryng holines to
the doers, ye life and ſaluacion. Thus decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers and pſeudoapoſtles, wente about to deceiue
theſe Coloſſia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and other, by tradicions of men, which are not to be obſerued, as
neceſſary for ſaluacion, purgers of ſynne, or ſatiſfaccion for ſinne bringers of
holines, or of eternal life: But as thynges indifferent, not to bee compared with Gods
commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, but to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued, as far as thei bee helpers to the keping of Gods
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dementes, and the fulfillyng of Gods will and pleaſure, and for good ordre and quietnes.
The fourthe thyng to bee ware of, is the Elementes of the worlde: by the Elementes, ſome
vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de
<pb facs="tcp:4757:70"/> the Su<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne, the Mone, the Ster<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, or the other elementes, thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng that there was
emonges the Coloſſia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, ſome that did wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhip theſe Elementes, as Gods, and deſired
health and ſalucaio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of theim, puttyng truſt and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in them, praiyng to them and
deſiryng of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> proſperous thynges, and of the diſpocicion of theſe Elementes,
Propheſied thynges to come. The Apoſtle here biddeth them bee ware, thei phantaſie none
ſuche thyng, by theſe Elementes, whiche are no Gods, nor are not to be worſhip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ped as God,
but as the creatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res of God, made and ordinated for the behaulfe and commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of man, in this
world: Other ſome vnderſtandeth by <hi>Elemen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ta mundi,</hi> the Ceremoniall, and
<pb facs="tcp:4757:71"/> Iudiciall lawes, of the old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, thynkyng the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for
ſaluacion, &amp; that none could be ſaued, without y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng of theim, as ſome thought
<hi>Act. xv.</hi> And emonges the Gala<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thians. <hi>Gala. iiii.</hi> But Peter and Iames, and the
reſidue of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles of Chriſt, thought legall Ceremonies and ſacrifices, not
neceſſarie for ſaluacion, but ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uacion mighte well enough bee had, without them, ye,
&amp; without al Ceremonies. For Ceremonies now vſed in the Churche, bee no holy thynges of
themſelfes, thei make no manne holy, thei bee no workers, nor workes of our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uacion, thei be
ordinated, to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie and repreſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, other thynges ſignified by theim. And here the
Apoſtle biddeth them beware, of
<pb facs="tcp:4757:71"/> ſuche as did call the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the lawe and not to Chriſte, to the Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies or
woorkes of the lawe, and of man decreed, and not of God commaunded: and here he willeth theim to
beware, of all theim that exhort men to Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, old cuſtomes, volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie woorkes, lawes,
ſtatutes, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees, tradicions of men, rather then Gods commaundementes.</p>
            <p n="3">3 For in Chriſt dwelleth al ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the Godhedde corporal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.) Now he ſheweth the
cauſe, why he moued theim too fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe Chriſt and his doctryne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, and none other doctryne,
contrary to this doctrine: it was becauſe all fulnes of God, as of holines, vertue, wiſedom,
grace, mercie, peace, goodnes, iuſtice, and of al perfeccion, did remain
<pb facs="tcp:4757:72"/> in Chriſt abundauntly and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitely, that it ſhould not nede to require, of any
other, any good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, holines, iuſtice, or righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, but of Chriſte onely and alone, of
whom is all goodnes, by whom, and in whom, equall to the father in ſubſtaunce, deite might and
power. By who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thei are fulfilled, with all goodnes, iuſtice, and righteouſnes, that thei haue
no neede to ſeke any good thyng of the lawe of woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, of the lawe of Ceremonies, or of
tradicions of men, for thei haue Chriſt in their hartes, roo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by true faithe, in the whiche,
is all the treaſures of the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God the father laied vp for vs, and in hym doth dwel
all fulnes of God the father, and he hath fulfilled all thynges, bothe
<pb facs="tcp:4757:72"/> the law, and the imperfeccion of the law, he hath taken it awaie, and made it
perfite, and vs by hym to performe the lawe.</p>
            <p>By whom you are cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed with circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion not made by handes when you put awaie the
bodye of ſynnes of the fleſhe, by the circumciſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Chriſte, buried toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with hym by
Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, in the whiche alſo, with hym, you haue riſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by faith of the woorke of God, whiche
hath raiſed hym from the dedde.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle ſheweth theſe Coloſſians, although thei were
<pb facs="tcp:4757:73"/> Gentiles, to be Circumciſed by Chriſte, not after the Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the
fleſhe, but by the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion of the ſpirite of God, without the handes of manne, whiche
he thought not neceſſary for theim, but that without the exterior Circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciſion of the
fleſhe the Gentiles might be ſaued, as well as the Iewes, that was cir<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cumciſed in the
fleſhe. And here he ſheweth two circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciſions, the one outwardes, made in the fleſh by
mennes handes, cuttyng a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waie a round pece of the ſkynne of the ſecrete members: and this
circumciſion, was not neceſſarie to ſaluacion, after the Goſpell was ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly preached,
after Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes paſſion, but was abrogated and left as indifferent, &amp; not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary
to ſaluacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: theother cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciſion,
<pb facs="tcp:4757:73"/> was the inward circum<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, by the ſpirit of God, by the whiche, the whole body
of ſynne, was mortified &amp; put awaie, cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely by the ſpirit, and by faith in Chriſt, and
this circumciſion is neceſſarie to ſaluacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: that is, by the ſpirite of God, to dye from
ſynne, and no more to returne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to ſynne, as Chriſte died once, and dieth no more, ſo
wee ſhould dye from ſinne, and ſinne no more, but walke alwaies in a newe life, and put on
Chriſt, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, truthe, iuſtice, and holines, and walke alwaie in theſe ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, followyng
Chriſte in all goodnes, and Godlines, in veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and iuſtice, and in cuttyng a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waie from the
harte, all euill de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, thoughtes, carnall affecci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, luſtes, and concupiſcenſes,
<pb facs="tcp:4757:74"/> whiche did ariſe of the fleſh, and not of the ſpirite of GOD, and this is the
Circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciſion of Chriſt whiche is our Baptiſme, by the whiche, we bee waſſhed from all our
ſinnes, by the workyng of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy Ghoſte in it, accordyng to the promiſe of God, and
therfore baptiſme is called, the waſſhyng of regeneracion, and renewyng of the holy ghoſte,
to <hi>Tite .iii.</hi> In the whiche baptiſme, we be pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from all our ſynnes. <hi>Ephe.
v</hi> By God inwardly workyng by his ſpirite, that cutteth from the harte all euil thoughtes,
carnal luſtes, and affeccions: and this is called the circumciſion of the harte, ſignified in
the olde lawe, by the outward Circumciſion of the fleſh. And this our baptiſme is come to vs,
in the ſtede of cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion
<pb facs="tcp:4757:74"/> to the Iewes, and is as neceſſarie, and more profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to vs, then was
Circumciſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the Iewes, in the tyme of the old law. And as it was neceſſary by Gods
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement. <hi>Gene. xvii.</hi> That all young men chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, ſhould be Circumciſed the
eighte daie: So it is no leſſe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie, that all young children ſhould be Baptiſed:
for without Baptiſme, none can bee ſaued. <hi>Ihon .iii. Math .xxviii. Marke .xvi.</hi>
Therfore the Anabaptiſtes, are greatly to bee blamed, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> would not haue young children,
Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtened, or Baptiſed in the water, and in the holy Ghoſt. Of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme of young
children, I haue ſpoken. <hi>Ephe. iiii.</hi> Therfore I do not ſpeake of it, in this place any
more.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:4757:75"/>And you whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you wer ded by ſynne, and by the vncircu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of your fleſh
together with hym, he hath quickened you aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, forgeuyng to you all youre ſynnes, and put
a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waie that hand writyng, that was againſt vs, con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teined in the lawe writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the decre,
that was contrary to vs, and that toke he clere awaye, and faſtened it to the croſſe, &amp;
hath ſpoyled Rule and power, and hath made a ſhewe of theim openly,
<pb facs="tcp:4757:75"/> and hath triu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>phed ouer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in his awne perſone.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle here ſheweth, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thyng that he ſhewed, more at large. <hi>Ephe. ii.</hi> That
is, what we are of our ſelfes, mightes, and powers, &amp; what we be by Chriſt. By our awne
nature, receiued of Adam, we wer ded by ſynne ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall, and of our ſelfes by actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
ſynne, but by Chriſte alone, we be reſtored again to life, and God hath forgeuen vs our
ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes frely, without our merites, or deſeruinges, for Chriſtes ſake onely, and where we
wer Genti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, vncircumciſed, now bee Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed in oure hartes, haue cutte awaie from our
hartes, all carnall affeccions, luſtes, &amp; ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petites, contrary to the ſpirite of
<pb facs="tcp:4757:76"/> GOD. And where as the hande writyng was againſt vs, that is where as the law
written, called hand written, did conuince vs of ſynne, that wee could not deny, but we wer
ſynners, and for our ſynne, had deſerued death, and we wer worthie death: yet it plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed
God, onely of his mere mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and grace, to forgeue vs our ſynnes, and to make vs heires of the
heauenly inheritau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and partakers of his glory, by Ieſus Chriſte. Alſo, where as the lawe
did condempne vs, for our ſyn to death, it pleaſed God of his mercie, not onely to forgeue vs
our ſynnes, but alſo to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waie that hande writyng, that conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pneth vs for ſynne to deth
and that writyng was the lawe of God written, that ſhewed all
<pb facs="tcp:4757:76"/> men to be ſynners, in the ſight of GOD, and no man to bee iuſte (Chriſte
onely excepted) in the ſight of God, and for ſinne wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie death. The Apoſtle here v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth
a Metaphor, of a writyng or of an obligacion made, where men be bound to fulfill the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng, or
obligacion made. This writing is the lawe of God, it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth that all men ſhould ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill the
lawe: no manne fulfilled the lawe (Chriſt onely excepted) wherefore al men was found by the lawe
gyltie, &amp; worthie death, becauſe thei fulfilled not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law, that thei were bounde to kepe.
This lawe, Chriſt not onely for himſelf, but for all them that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue in hym, or ſhall
beleue in hym, to the worldes ende, did ful<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fill, that it ſhall not bee imputed
<pb facs="tcp:4757:77"/> to theim, that beleue in Chriſte, any traſgreſſion of the lawe, for Chriſt
is the fulfiller of the law, and we by hym, &amp; in hym, Chriſt is the perfeccion of the lawe,
to al the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that beleue in hym. <hi>Ro. x.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 He hath faſtened it to the croſſe.) Now he ſheweth when he deliuered vs from
ſynne, and brake in peces the Obligacion, that condempneth vs to death, for ſynne: it was whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
he ſuffered death vpon the croſſe for vs, and toke our ſynnes vpon his backe <hi>Eſay.
liii.</hi> And in that ſuffryng he ouercame the deuill, and all our enemies, ſynne, death, and
hell, and the deuill, and all wicked ſpirites, whom he calleth here, rule and power, and in token
of victorie, he ſprede abrode ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of victorie, and the ſpoyles
<pb facs="tcp:4757:77"/> of enemies diuided, and did tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph noblely ouer his enemies and that by no other
power or mighte, but by his awne power and might, and ſtrength, that al honor and glory, ſhould
be geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to God alone, and to none other for all victories had ouer our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, to declare vnto
vs, by whom, and in whoſe name and power, wee ſhall ouercome oure enemies, the deuill, the
worlde, and the fleſhe, that is, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of Chriſte, and by Chriſte alone, and not by
holy water ſprynke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng, or by the ſound of an holy bell, by a palme croſſe, holy can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle,
or other ſorcery or witcherie, as ſome foliſhly and ſuperſtici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly hath thought: for
theſe ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not driue awaie the deuill, but rather the deuill is kepte, and
<pb facs="tcp:4757:78"/> mainteined, by ſuche falſe tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes, vain hope &amp; lies: for Chriſt droue
not away the deuill, when he was te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pted of the deuill. <hi>Mat. iiii.</hi> With holy water, holy
can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, palmes, or croſſes, but by the woorde of GOD, reſiſtyng all temptacions of the
deuil, and ſo by the woorde of God, muſte we reſiſt and ouercome the deuill. <hi>Epheſi.
vi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore, let no man iudge you in meate or drynke, or in parte of the holy daie, as the newe
Moone or Sabboth da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yes, which are ſhadowes of thynges to come, the body verely is of
Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle ſemeth here, to
<pb facs="tcp:4757:78"/> gather a concluſion, of the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des and ſentences goyng before after this maner:
foraſmuche as Chriſt hath reſtored you ded, to life again, and hath circumciſed your
hartes, and forgeuen you all your ſynnes, and take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> awaie that hande writyng, that conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pned
you to death, for ſin in you ye, and alſo hath ouercomed all your aduerſaries, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was
againſt you, or would haue accuſed yon, and hath had victorie ouer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And alſo you in
Chriſt haue all iuſtice, holines, wiſedome, forge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenes of ſynne, redempcion, ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uacion,
life, and all perfeccion, fredom from al captiuitie of the deuill, ſynne, death, or hell fire:
from all ſeruitude and bondage of the lawe, and that by Chriſte onely, that you hauyng and
poſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeſſyng
<pb facs="tcp:4757:79"/> Chriſte, by true faithe, haue no nede of the lawe, or wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes of it, that you
ſhould not thynke the lawe neceſſary to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uacion: that is, that you ſhould not thynke,
that without you kepe the lawe, and all the Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of it, you could not bee ſaued, as ſome
thought, no man could be ſaued, without he were Circumciſed in the fleſhe, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng to the
old lawe. <hi>Gene. xvii.</hi> Commaunded to Abraham, and his poſteritie, duryng the tyme of the
law: but againſt that opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, ſaincte Paule throughout all his Epiſtles, laboreth and
ſheweth plainly, that Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is not neceſſary to ſaluacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but that without
Circumciſion, and workes of the lawe, ſuch as beleue in Chriſte, ſhalbee ſaued,
<pb facs="tcp:4757:79"/> although thei neuer were Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed. Ye, alſo he declareth plainly, the lawe
and the woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of the lawe, as Ceremonies, and Iudicialles, not to bee kept vnder the pain of
dampnacion, and as neceſſarie to ſaluacion, as without theim, no man could bee ſaued,
whiche ſaincte Paule here improueth, and willeth that no man ſhould iudge another, good or bad,
for meate or drinke forbidden in the Lawe of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, or for kepyng of holy daies, or not for
kepyng holy daies, as Sabboth daies, feaſtes of newe Moones, or other holy daies, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded by
the lawe, whiche if thei bee kepte as indifferent thynges, thei make no manne good, iuſt, or
holy, for kepyng of them, nor yet thei condempne no
<pb facs="tcp:4757:80"/> man, if thei bee necglected or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, and lefte vndoen: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no man ſhould
iudge ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, good or euill, for dooyng or omittyng theſe workes, abroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Chriſte, and
left to vs as workes indifferent.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Lette no manne iudge you, in meat or drynke.) Now he taketh away all holines, from meate
or drynke, willyng that no manne ſhould coumpt holines, to be in meate and drynke, or in
abſtey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng from the ſame, for the kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gdom of GOD, is not meate or drinke, but iuſtice,
peace, and ioy in the holy ghoſt. <hi>Rom. xiii.</hi> And here he would no manne ſhould iudge
another good, for abſtey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng from meate or drynke, or euill, for eatyng of meate, and drinkyng
of drynke. This place
<pb facs="tcp:4757:80"/> doth ſhewe, that by Gods lawe, meate and drynke are not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden, to bee eaten of
any man, nor GOD careth not, what maner of meate a man eate, ſo he eate it with ſobrietie, with
ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng of tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes to God for it, as to the onely aucthor and geuer of all meate, to all creatures
for the neceſſities of manne, to fede the body, that it maie be able to ſerue God, and to do
the workes of the ſpirite. Learne, that it is not the meate, that entereth into a manne, that
defileth hym, but that goeth out fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> man, defileth man, as euill thoughtes, wordes and deedes,
adultery, fornicacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> murther. &amp;c. <hi>Mat. xv.</hi> Alſo, learne here, that there is no
maner of meate, forbidden Chriſtians, to eate by Gods lawe, ſo thei eate
<pb facs="tcp:4757:81"/> with ſobrietie, and with thankes geuyng to God: yet Chriſtians may not vſe
alwaie, this their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie, for three or foure cauſes. Firſte, the ordinaunce of hye po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers,
whiche hath decreed ſome daies of abſteine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, from this or that kynde of meate, to this
or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinaunce of hye powers, it beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth euery one to bee obedient, and to kepe their ordinaunces,
as long as thei would haue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> kepte, as thynges expedient for the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wealth, peace, iuſtice
and good ordre, or for good pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litique endes. As the abſteine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce from fleſhe, the tyme of
Lente, whiche is an ordinaunce admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of manne, and of hie powers and rulers, for many good
cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and conſideracions, &amp; when it ſhall pleace the hie powers, to
<pb facs="tcp:4757:81"/> abrogate and take awaie, that ordinaunce of the faſte of Lent, the hye powers maie
lawfully take it away, as thei ſhal thinke mete and expedient, for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth, and yet no
parte of Gods lawe taken awaie. Many cauſes I thynke did moue the rulers of the common wealth, to
inſtitute abſtinence, from fleſhe in Lent tyme. Firſt, becauſe that that time of the
yere, fleſhe is for the more parte out of ſeaſon, and not wholeſome for mannes bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, and
for the more health of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in their bodies, after Eaſter, when thei ſhal eate fleſhe again.
Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly, that men ſhould more chaſtice their bodies, that thei beyng faſtyng or kepyng
abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence, ſhould with more earneſt, and inwarde affeccion, praie to
<pb facs="tcp:4757:82"/> God for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelfes, and for other: for ful belies, ſeldo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> geue feruent praier to
God, or tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes hartie, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his harte, to God for his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefites. Thirdly, that by abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce,
men ſhould the better mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie, &amp; ouercome al carnal affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions. Fourthly, becauſe this
time of Le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, is a time for beaſtes to brede in, &amp; thei ſhould be ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that tyme, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
more ſtore of cat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tell ſhould be al the yere after, &amp; ſo of more ſtore &amp; plentie,
cattell ſhould bee better chepe. Fifthly, that by abſtinence of Lent, men ſhould mortifie
their carnall af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and be made more pure, and cleane in conſcience, againſt Eaſter,
y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei mighte at Eaſter, receiue worthely, the body and bloud of Chriſte. For theſe and
many other cauſes, expedient for
<pb facs="tcp:4757:82"/> commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wealthes, I thynke this time of Lent was inſtituted, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> old fathers of
the churche, &amp; not that the faſt of Le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, ſhould iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, make them holy and
good, take away ſinnes, or ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie for ſynnes, or that the eatyng of fiſhe ſhould
make a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> better before god, then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eating of fleſh by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> outward worke in it ſelf, as
ſome hath taughte, conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pnyng them for heretiques and lollars that eate but white meate in Le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t
ſeaſon, neuer generally forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyn by any lawe, to bee eaten in this Realme: for in the Northe
partes alwaie, the people did eate white meate in Lent ſeaſon, without any prohibicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to them
by the lawe. But this falſe iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement of Lente, that it ſhould be, by Gods lawe commaunded
<pb facs="tcp:4757:83"/> or that it was a Tradicion of Chriſte, or of his Apoſtles, that it was
neceſſarily to bee obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, vnder the pain of dampna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, that it iuſtified menne, toke
awaie ſinnes, made men holy, or better then other, was a falſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of Lent, not grounded
v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon holy ſcripture: But this is come to ignorau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t men, by igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of holy ſcripture, mete
and worthie to be improued, and ſpo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken again, of all true preachers, paſtors, and Curates, and
of all men. And although God hath not appoynted to vs, any diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of meate in daies, but
ſaith, that all maner of meate is pure, to theim that bee pure, and that doth eate with genyng of
than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, to the lorde for their meate. <hi>i. Timo. iii.</hi> And that it is not the
<pb facs="tcp:4757:83"/> meate, that entereth into a man, that defileth a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but it is that goeth out of the
mouth, that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fileth a man. <hi>Math. xv.</hi> Yet there is three or foure thynges, that prohibeth
men, to vſe their liber<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie in meate and drinke. Firſt, is the ordinaunce of the high po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers,
to whom it becommeth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery ſubiect, to be obedient in al lawfull ordinau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, and cauſes, not
contrary to Goddes lawe. The ſeconde, is the infirmitie or weakenes, of our brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whom we may
not offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, by our meate and drinke. <hi>Ro. xiiii.</hi> The third, is a conſcience erronious,
thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng not lawfull to eate meate, and yet againſt his conſcience doth eate: that man that
ſo doth, offendeth God. <hi>Nam qui contra conſcientiam edit, peccat. Ro. xiiii.
<pb facs="tcp:4757:84"/> i. Corin. viii.</hi> His conſcience erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious, ſhould bee rectified, and then
let hym eate with a ſtreight conſcience, rectified after true knowlege of Gods worde. The
fourth, maie be for health of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes body, to preſerue it from ſic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenes. Fifthly, to mortifie
car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall affeccions, luſtes, and deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, and to make the bodie, obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to the ſpirite of
God, and to doo the workes of the ſpirite. This is alwaie to be noted and obſerued, that no man
vſe his li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie, in meate, drynke, and in other indifferent thinges, to ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill the deſires
of the fleſhe, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che thyng many doeth, by whom the worde of God, ſuffreth euill, and is euill
ſpoken of, emonges Heathen, ye, emonges chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and many be offended, iudgyng
<pb facs="tcp:4757:84"/> other with them. And ſuche peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple iudge ſome to do euill, when in eatyng thei
doo not euill, but that thei maie dooe lawfully, by Gods lawe, and thei that euill iudgeth,
offendeth God, and not thei that eate, with a rectified co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, geuyng thankes to God
knowyng all meates pure to the pure.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Or in part of the holy daie, or new Moone, or of Sabboth da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yes.) He forbiddeth one to
iudge another, for kepyng of the holy daie, or not for kepyng of it. Of the Sabboth daie, it is
written. <hi>Leuiti. xxiii.</hi> and for what intent thei were inſtitute: thei were or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinated,
that the people ſhould reſt, from all their bodily labors and come together, in a mete and
conuenient place, to here the
<pb facs="tcp:4757:85"/> woorde of GOD, to learne to knowe God, and theimſelfes, to glorifie God, to praie
vnto God one for another, to geue than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes to God, for his benefites, to them and to other, to
receiue the benefites, of the ſacramentes of God, and that theſe daies ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, men
ſhould ceaſſe from all ſeruile workes: that is, from all ſinne, and to ſerue GOD truly,
after that ſort, as God hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted to bee ſerued, honored, and worſhipped of all menne,
in his holy ſcriptures. But alacke for pitie, no daie God is ſerued worſe, then vpon the holy
daie, in many places, what eatyng, drynkyng, riotyng, and ſurfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng, cardyng and diſyng,
ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng, and blaſphemyng the holy name of God, is vpon holy da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yes,
<pb facs="tcp:4757:85"/> it greueth euery good man to here it, ſee it, or to ſpeake of it, whiche is
vſed more vpon the holy daie, then vpon the woorke daie. I will not ſpeake of the dru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kennes,
of the vnthriftie ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng, of mennes ſubſtaunce, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the holy daie, ye, more then thei
can get, the whole weke be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: ye, parauenture ſome thyng of the weeke folowyng, ſhalbee
ſpente, or it bee gotten, and that when no nede requireth. It is no merueill, though God doth
ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fre ſuche vnthriftes, ſome tyme to neede neceſſarie thynges, in puniſhment of their
ſynnes, and yet parauenture, ſuche vnthrif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and drunkers, thynketh thei kepe the holy daie
well, if thei abſtein fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> handie labors. I wil not ſpeake of adulterie, fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<pb facs="tcp:4757:86"/> ſlaundryng, backbityng one another: of craft, falſhed, deceipt vſurie,
periurie, contencion, and debate, vſed vpon the holy daie, by the whiche, the holy daie is
broken, rather then by handie woorke, neceſſarie to be doen, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the holy daie, and yet the
ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly daie not broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but kept: God graunte that the holy daie maye be ſpente, as Gods woorde
wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth and commaundeth. Alſo he willeth, that no man ſhall iudge another, for feaſtes of
new Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: Feaſtes of newe Moones, was celebrated euery monethe, aſſone as the newe Moone
did appere: for it doeth appere, that theſe Coloſſia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, worſhipped the Moone as a GOD, and
gaue Godly honor to it, whiche thyng the Apoſtle forbiddeth, and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth
<pb facs="tcp:4757:86"/> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not to honor the Moone as a God, for it is no God, but the creature of God,
ordinated for the commoditie of man: nor to kepe holy daies, to honor the newe Moone, nor yet to
doo any ſacrifice, to any Idolle, as the Heathen did. Al ſuche falſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippyng of
creatures, for God, is here forbidden, as thynges vnlawfull, diſpleaſyng God: or to kepe holy
daie in their names or for their ſakes, to do ſacrifice to theim, to honor theim, or wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
theim.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Which are ſhadowes of thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to come, the body verely of Chriſte.) As he ſhould
ſaie, dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of meates in daies, ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyng of holy daies, as of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> newe Moone, of the
Tabernacle, of Paſche, of Pentecoſte, and ſuche
<pb facs="tcp:4757:87"/> like, are but ſhadowes of thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges for to come, and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies do come, of
whiche thei wer ſhadowes, then ceaſeth the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes: when the thing commeth it ſelf, then
ceaſeth the figure, the thyng it ſelf is come, lette vs care no more for the figure, wee haue
the body, fare well the ſhadowe: Theſe figures and ſhadowes in the old lawe, thei figured
Chriſt the ſauiour of the worlde to come thei figured y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſhould, ſpryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle his bloud
vpon the Croſſe, for the redempcion, and ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the world, Chriſt is come, and hath
ſhed his bloudde for our redempcion, and by hym a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, we be ſaued: therefore ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes and
figures, muſte nowe ceaſe, and no more be coumpted, as neceſſarie to bee kepte, to our
<pb facs="tcp:4757:87"/> ſaluacion, for without theim, we be brought to ſaluacion, that is, by the mercie,
grace, and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of God the father, for Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes ſake alone, and not for oure merites, or
deſeruynges.</p>
            <p>Let no man make you ſhote at a wrong marke, after his awne choſyng, walkyng in humblenes and
ſuperſticion of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelles, in thoſe thynges which thei haue not ſene goyng vainly, puft vp,
of the mynde of their fleſhe, not obeiyng their hed, of whiche the whole bodie by ioyntes, and
couples, fixed and ioyned, recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth
<pb facs="tcp:4757:88"/> nouriſhement, and doeth increaſe by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſement of God.</p>
            <p>Now more at large he moni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth theim, to bee ware of pſeu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doapoſtles, &amp; craftie
deceiuers, whom he ſetteth furthe in their colours, mouyng theim to bee ware of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that
ſtudy to plucke awaie from theim, their rewarde thei looke for, and to geue theim pain for ioye,
ſhadowes for the thynges, figures for the veritie, darkenes for lighte, ſhadowes for the
bodies, yearthly thynges for heauenly thynges, carnall thynges, for ſpirituall thynges. Note here
how falſe Apoſtles, &amp; deceiptfull iugglers, go aboute to deceiue theim, and turneth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waie
from men, their heauenly
<pb facs="tcp:4757:88"/> reward: ſuche be thei, that teache Moſes for Chriſt, workes of the lawe, for
the Goſpell, and woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of the ſpirite, for true faithe in Chriſt, Ceremonies, and ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
ordinaunces, and tradicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of like neceſſitie to Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes, to be obſerued, or
els of more neceſſitie. And in this, theſe falſe Apoſtles, are more to be blamed, that
thei doo it of a ſet purpoſe and mynd, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſedly intendyng, to deceiue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and in this
their malice, is more to bee noted and reproued, that thei ſtudie to deceiue other, and to plucke
other from the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Goſpell, into hereſies: ſuche bee thei, that ſtifly defende
workes of the lawe, to be kept of neceſſitie of ſaluacion, as Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, Ceremonies,
and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:4757:89"/> mennes tradicions, to be ob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſerued of like neceſſitie, as the commaundementes
of GOD, &amp; more eſteme mannes tradicions then Gods commaundementes, thoſe bee thei, whiche
Paule in this place, biddeth vs beware of, for thei goo aboute to plucke away from vs, our heauenly
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde.</p>
            <p n="2">2 By humilitie and ſuperſticio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Angels.) Here he ſheweth by what meanes thei went
aboute to deceiue them: that was, by hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie, pretendyng great humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie and mekenes, contempte
of the worlde, of worldely honors and promocions, conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt of car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall pleaſures and riches, in
ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite, countenaunce, and goyng, ſad and deuoutely, pretendyng great holines and perfeccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and

<pb facs="tcp:4757:89"/> nothyng els but holines, they would be ſene to menne to haue, and yet thei were
inwardly, Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrytes, diſſemblers, full of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, malice, and enuie, full of pompe and
pride, coueteous and vainglorious, ye, verie greedy Wolfes, clothed in ſhepes ſkyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, that
thei might, by that mea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, the ſoner deceiue the ſimple: as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuill tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſfigureth
hymſelf, into an Angell of lighte, that he ſhould deceiue the ſoner, the ſim<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple: ſo the
Wolfe commeth clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed in a ſhepe ſkinne, and ſo ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner deceiue the ſhepe, then if he
came openly, as a Wolfe in a Wolfe ſkynne: So fained holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and pretenſed ſanctite,
decei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueth many. Alſo, pſeudoapoſtles went about, to deceiue theſe Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſſians, by
religion of Angels,
<pb facs="tcp:4757:90"/> as the olde tranſlacion hath: E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſmus, by ſuperſticion of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels. What
ſaincte Paule mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth here, I cannot well tell, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepte he meane, that falſe Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,
phantaſied ſome hye honor and worſhip, to be geuen to holy Angelles, if thei kepte the lawe,
geuen by the miniſtracion of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Angels: and thoſe to diſpleaſe the Angelles that kepte
not the lawe, geuen by Angels: and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Angels to honor the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued the Lawe ſo thei
taught: the Angelles of God, to venge their iniuries and diſpleaſures, in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that did not
kepe the lawe of Moſes. So theſe pſeudoapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles taught it, to bee a worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyng of
Angelles, to obſerue the lawe, and the workes of the law as neceſſarie to ſaluacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whiche

<pb facs="tcp:4757:90"/> thyng, ſainct Paule coumpteth here, no honor nor worſhippe of Angels, but
ſuperſticion of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, a pretenſe to honor Angels and do diſhonor them, and moſt rebuke
to Angels, that can bee doen. Or els this place, maye be otherwiſe expounded, after this maner,
that ſome pſeudoapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, emong theſe Coloſſians, ſtudied to deceiue them: ſaiyng,
thei were the Angelles of God, ſente from God aboue, and that thei had receiued, certain
viſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of angels, and of holy ſpirites in ſome oracles, wherein thei were ſhewed the will
and pleaſure of God, and what god would haue doen of menne in the yearth, and that was, that thei
muſte nedes kepe the lawe of Moſes, and the woorkes of it, or els thei ſaied,
<pb facs="tcp:4757:91"/> thei could not bee ſaued, whiche thyng, ſainct Paule improueth, in all his
Epiſtles, but moſte plainly it is improued, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pned of the Apoſtles of Chriſt
<hi>Act .xv.</hi> Suche pſeudoapoſtles, was emo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges vs ſome tyme, that ſaid, holy Angels,
holy ſpirites, and ſoules of men departed, to haue appered vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that thei ſhould goo
this pilgrimage, or that pilgrimage, to this Image or that image, in ſuche a place, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei
ſhould cauſe to bee ſaied or ſong ſo many Diriges, ſo many Maſſes found ſuche a
fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for Maſſes for preſcript praiers purchaſe ſuche pardons, &amp; ſuche
indulgences: and many like Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelacions, hath been ſhewed to men, as pſeudoapoſtles ſaied,
by the whiche meanes thei deceiued
<pb facs="tcp:4757:91"/> many, of a long tyme, but than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes be to God, their deceipte is knowen, in a maner to
all men, how vain and fooliſhe it was, &amp; how vngodly, and how perilous and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to mannes
ſaluacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and how it came not of God, but of the deuill, &amp; was inuented of men, &amp;
mainteined for lucre ſake.</p>
            <p n="3">3 In thoſe thynges, whiche thei haue not ſene.) As he would ſay, this deceiuer
feineth hymſelf, to haue ſene in viſion many thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, whiche he hath not ſene, and to haue
heard many thynges, whiche he hath not heard, and to haue larned many thynges, whiche he hath not
learned, as ſome haue feined them, to bee in a traunce, and in it to haue ſene, the ioyes of
heauen, the peines of purgatorie (as thei liyng, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb facs="tcp:4757:92"/> it) and of hell, and by what meanes, men ſhould haue been deliuered out of
purgatory, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thei did ſee, or heard none ſuche thynges. And for this ende, thei feined
ſuche ſightes, for lucre ſake, and that thei ſhould bee coumpted of men, not as mortal men,
but rather as Goddes, and men worthie that holy Angelles ſhould come to theim, and ſpeke to
theim Goddes will and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and that thei were worthie, to be canonized for ſainctes, and
of all menne eſtemed holy men: and yet ſainct Paule, calleth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> here deceiuers, and to go
proud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as thoſe that plaie in ſtage plaies, Princes, or Kynges, or Goddes, beyng no ſuche
thyng, as thei pretende to bee. In this place, the Apoſtle ſemeth to me,
<pb facs="tcp:4757:92"/> to make an anſwere, to the ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng of pſeudoapoſtles, ſeeyng that thei bee
the Angelles, and meſſengers of god, and that thei do exhorte men to thoſe thynges, that God
commaundeth by his holy Angelles, that is, to the ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyng of the lawe, and of workes of the Lawe,
and that thei that kept the law, did honor Angels, and the breakers of the lawe did not honor, but
diſpiſed Angels, and God alſo, whoſe meſſengers the Angelles was, and that thei were
ſure, their doctryne to bee true, becauſe thei had it of the Angelles of GOD? To this ſainct
Paule anſwereth, ſaiyng: that thei exhorte men, vnto that thyng thei knowe not, whiche thei
nether haue ſeen, nor harde, for thei knowe not (ſaieth he) the
<pb facs="tcp:4757:93"/> law, and the workes of the law, to be ſhadowes and figures, ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen for a tyme, till
the body and veritie did come, &amp; then to ceaſe and to bee no more, as neceſſarie to
ſaluacion: now the body and veritie is come, whiche is Chriſt our ſauior, whiche theſe
ſhado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes and figures did repreſente. Therefore, the lawe is not now to be kept of
neceſſitie, to ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and that is the chief matter, that ſainct Paule here laboreth,
ſo diligently to teache, &amp; to haue it perſwaded to al men. Se how earneſtly euill men,
went aboute in Paules tyme, to teache falſe doctrine, and how thei ſaied, thei had it of
Angelles, and the true worſhip of God and of Angels to be in it, and God and his holy Angelles to
bee diſhonored, if
<pb facs="tcp:4757:93"/> their doctryne were not kepte. Paule ſaith, thei knew not what thei ſpake, and
that thei walked vainly, and to no profit, and yet thei were proude men, proude of their doctryne,
auauncyng them ſelfes of it. Like to theim hath been in oure daies, teachers of pilgrimages, of
Maſſes of <hi>ſcala caeli,</hi> patrons of purgatorie, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inteiners of worſhippyng of
I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, &amp; defenders of them, thei wer thei of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Paule ſpeaketh <hi>i. Timo. i.</hi> Thei
knewe not what thei ſpake, and affirmeth to bee true, which thei knewe not to be true, nor of
what foundacion, it hath his truthe: all ſuche decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, ſainct Paule here ſharpely
reproueth. He ſaieth, thei goo proudly, bearyng an hye coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunce, as all the worlde were
<pb facs="tcp:4757:94"/> theirs, as all learnyng ſhould hang at their ſleues, &amp; thei onely and none
els, to be defenders of faith, and of al godly learnyng, and yet ſainct Paule ſaieth, thei go
in vain, thei profite neither the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelfes, nor other, thei be pufte vp, with the wiſedo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the
fleſhe, and thynke the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelfes to haue all learnyng, when thei do not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande, thoſe
thynges they ſpeke of and affirme, with great audacitie &amp; boldnes as thei wer in Goddes
boſome: thei ſeke not the glory of God, but their awne glory and profite, and thei fein them to
haue had, viſions of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, of holy ſainctes, reuelaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, for pilgrimages, Pardons,
paintyng of ſtockes and bloc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, ſuche was the holy maide of Kent, whoſe craft and deceipt,
<pb facs="tcp:4757:94"/> is knowen almoſte to all menne how ſhe deceiued many.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Thei doo not obtein the hed, in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the whole body by ioyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, and couples ioyned,
increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth by the increaſeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of God.) Here is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſe ſhewed, of their deceipte, the
cauſe is, that they haue not Chriſte, thei ſeeke not Chriſte, the hed of the Churche, thei
haue not Chriſt, alwaies be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore their iyes, thei ſeke not his glory, but their awne glory,
thei referre not all thynges thei haue receiued to Chriſt, but to other, as to angelles, to
ſpirites, to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfes, their merites, or to the me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rites of other, and not to Chriſt,
whiche is our whole health, life, perfeccion, and ſaluacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is all goodnes laied vp for
vs, and without whom, there is no
<pb facs="tcp:4757:95"/> goodnes commyng to vs, and in Chriſt all good thynges increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, to a ful
perfeccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Chriſte, no good thyng in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth, or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to perfeccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>wherfore, if you be ded with Chriſt, from the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lementes of this worlde, why as liuyng in the
worlde, are you holden with ſuch tradicions, as though you liued in the worlde? Thou ſhalt not
touche, thou ſhalte not taſte, nor handle, whiche all thynges doo hurte to ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, becauſe of
the abuſe, of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes
<pb facs="tcp:4757:95"/> and doctrines of menne, hauyng a pretenſe of wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedom, by ſuperſticio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and
humilitie of mynde, and da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mage of the body, and not by honor, to the ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiyng of the
fleſhe.</p>
            <p>Paule moueth theſe Coloſſia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to returne no more to thinke, the lawe or woorkes of it,
neceſſarie to ſaluacion, or dampnable to omit it, after this maner. If you be ded with
Chriſte, from the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lementes of the worlde: that is, from the lawe, and from the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies,
ſacrifices, and Iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, why as you were vnder the lawe, do you ſo muche
regarde the lawe, and thynke you ſhalbee dampned, if you kepe not the Lawe? Hath
<pb facs="tcp:4757:96"/> not Chriſte redemed you? And broughte you to healthe, to life, and to ſaluacion,
and to all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feccion, that you nede no help of the lawe, to obtein any holines, goodnes, or any
perfeccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? The lawe brought you to no holines nor could geue you no holines, why wil you then
forſake Chriſt the aucthor of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all goodnes commeth, &amp; runne vnto the law, and require
of it iuſtice, &amp; righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes, that ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not geue to you thoſe thynges? Therefore, for as
muche, as the lawe is abrogated by Chriſte, why will ye turne to it again, and thynke it
neceſſary for ſaluacion? For by Chriſte, is life and ſaluacion, without all helpe of the
lawe. As Paule here reproued y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pſeudoapoſtles: ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng, no manne could bee ſaued,
<pb facs="tcp:4757:96"/> without the lawe, and the woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of the lawe, and thoſe thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges that were
commaunded in the lawe: ſo he reproueth thoſe men that ſaie, men cannot be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, excepte
thei kepe mannes tradicions, as neceſſarie for ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uacion, as Gods commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, whiche
thyng, Chriſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proueth in the Phariſeis. <hi>Math. xv.</hi> Callyng theim Hypocrytes,
breaking Goddes commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, for their tradicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che thei preferred, aboue Gods
commaundementes, or els made the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> equall, with Gods commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dementes. Paule here dooth not
condempne, Ciuill ordinaunces and ſtatutes, that proueth Gods woorde and glorie, that cauſeth
peace, and concorde, equitie, and iuſtice, and a good ordre, emon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
<pb facs="tcp:4757:97"/> the people of God, and that moueth men, to vertue and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines, all ſuche lawes or
Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions, he approueth, but he will that no Ordinaunce of manne, ſhould be preferred, aboue
God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des Lawe, or made equall with Gods commaundementes, nor iuſtice, holines, righteouſnes, to
be required of mannes Lawes, Tradicions, or of Ceremonies, inuented and made by man.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2</hi> Thou ſhalte not touche, thou ſhalte not taſte, thou ſhalte not handle.)
Paule ſpeaketh here, in the perſone of Pſeudoapoſtles, whiche ſtudie to bryng,
Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans from Chriſte, to Ieweſhnes again: ſaiyng, thou ſhalte not touche vncleane
thinges, as ded bodies, or leproſe (by the whiche is ſignified in the lawe, ſynnes,
<pb facs="tcp:4757:97"/> or vncleane vices, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei ſhould not be committed, thou ſhalt not taſt this
meate, for it is vnclene, and forbidden to be eaten. Mea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes of themſelfes, was neuer vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane:
But thei were called vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane, for twoo cauſes, the one was, that the lawe did forbid, to eate
them, and ſo thei wer called vncleane: the other was, for ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnificacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of an vncleane thyng
that was ſignified by it: But nowe, no maner of meates, is vncleane, to them that be cleane
<hi>Tite. i. omnia munda mundis.</hi> All thynges are pure and cleane, to theim that bee cleane,
and are to be receiued, with geuyng of tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes to God, except Maieſtrates do commaunde the
contrary, or the infirmitie or weakenes, of oure brother, or oure erronious
<pb facs="tcp:4757:98"/> conſcience do will the contrary, for theſe cauſes, a man muſt ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtein from
his libertie in meates and not vſe it at all tymes. Men ſhould not put holines, in
abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence from meate, or ſinne in ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſoberly, with geuyng of tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes to God, for the
kyngdome of God, is not meate and drynke, but iuſtice, peace, and ioye in the holy Ghoſt.
<hi>Rom. xiiiii.</hi> Euen ſo it was with vs, in tymes paſte. Was it not forbidden, to touche
this holy veſſell, vnder pain of ſuſpenſion, or dedly ſynne? And to eate meate
permitted of God, was it not coumpted worſe, then to breake Goddes commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes? As vpon the
Fridaie, to eate white meate, as egges, but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and Cheſe, was eſtemed as greate an offence,
as Thefte
<pb facs="tcp:4757:98"/> murder, adulterie, theſe was not coumpted ſo greate an offence, before God, as to
eate fleſhe, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the Fridaie, or in Le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t tyme, although he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> did eate fleſh, was ſicke,
or by Maieſtrates lice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſed, that was cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pted ſuch a great &amp; abhominable offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, before
God that GOD could not, or rather would not, forgeue that offence, and ſuche was more abhorred of
menne, then he that had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted thefte, murder, and adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie: but thankes be to God, for right
knowlege now geuen, and let euery one vſe their knowlege and Chriſtian libertie, to Gods glory,
to the profite of their nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghbors, &amp; not to ſatiſfie the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall appetites, luſtes, and
deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res of the fleſhe, for if we liue af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the fleſhe, we ſhal dye. <hi>Ro. viii</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:4757:99"/> But if we ſhall mortifie, the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feccions of the fleſhe, by the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of
God, we ſhal liue. <hi>Ro. viii</hi> And optein life eternall. <hi>Gala. vi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 All theſe do periſhe in the vſe, after the preceptes and doctrine of men.) He
ſpeaketh of meates, whiche after thei be eaten do pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhe: that is, thei go into the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
and ſome parte fedeth the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and other part goeth into the excrementes, and thoſe meates,
bryng in ſynne, and death, if thei be eaten, or abſteined fro, as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for
ſaluacion, or cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pted dedly ſynne, to eate theim nowe, after the Goſpell ſhewed, for it is
not the preceptes, or doctryne of man, that maketh a man holy or vnholy, but it is the kepyng of
Goddes commaundementes, that maketh a man acceptable
<pb facs="tcp:4757:99"/> to God, whiche no man can doo, without Gods fauor and grace. Meate is abuſed, if
men do put holines, iuſtice, vertue, righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, life, &amp; ſaluacion, in meates, or in
abſteinyng fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or think ſynne in eatyng theim ſoberly, with thankes to God: as ſome
hath put, greate holines in fiſhe, and ſynne in eatyng of fleſh, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as holines before GOD,
is no more in eatyng of fleſhe, then of fiſh, ſo he that eateth, do not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempne any
ordinanunces, of hye powers, and without offence, of the weake in knowlege, and for to ſerue God,
with all goodnes: ſo thynges that bee indifferent, of theimſelfes, if thei bee taught as
neceſſary to bee kept for ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uacion, or that it is dedly ſynne, to omitte them, then thei
are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb facs="tcp:4757:100"/> to periſhe. For then thei doo hurte, then thei are not taken, as thei ſhould bee
taken: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Apoſtle ſaieth here, that thei doo periſhe, becauſe thei are not
taken, as thinges indiffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Whiche hath a pretence of wiſedom, by ſuperſticio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blenes of mynde, and by
hurt of the body.) He ſaieth, that the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctryne of Pſeudoapoſtles, had a ſimilitude, or
likenes, or appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce, of holines, but not holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in deede, &amp; that apparaunce it had, by
three thynges ſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. That was, of ſuperſticion, of humblenes of mynd, &amp; of greate
puniſhement of the body. Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſticion, was, when thei feined to theimſelf, a waie of
holines, whiche thei followed, makyng theim holy, followyng that vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary
<pb facs="tcp:4757:100"/> Religion, or Godlines, inuented by theimſelfes, by men or by mannes Tradicions,
Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrynes, or Ceremonies, thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> to bee, a more truer wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping of god, then to
worſhip God, as was appointed, to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe God, in holy ſcriptures. And of this ſort,
there was verie many, that were coumpted holy, and more holy then other was, onely for kepyng of
ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicions and ordinaunces, as of this ſorte, was many Religious men, called holy, rather
then for kepyng of Goddes commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dementes, whiche thei ſkarcely knewe, and yet thei were
coum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted holy men, before the world: but this holines, was no holines before God, but plain
ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, &amp; to this holines, I would
<pb facs="tcp:4757:101"/> ſaie ſuperſticion, men was more ready to, then to bee holy before God, in
kepyng Goddes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes. The ſecond cauſe, why the doctryne of pſeudoapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,
appered holy, was becauſe thei that preached, appered hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and meke, before the worlde, and
contempners of the worlde, and of worldely honors and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches: diſpiſers of carnall
plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and luſtes, was thoughte to care for no worldly thing, but for God, and for
heauenly thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and yet thei were inwardly, vain glorious, and would bee coumpted holy, and
good, iuſte, and righteous, that had deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued heauen, and heauen to bee their awne, for their
merites, and deſeruynges, and onely for ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyng, of mannes tradicions, ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies,
<pb facs="tcp:4757:101"/> and other inuencions of man, of the whiche, commeth no holines before God, but
ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſticio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The third thyng, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>by Pſeudoapoſtles appered ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, was by their greate
pain, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors, and abſtinence thei tooke in their bodies, as by greate fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyng, long praiyng,
and greate watchyng, riſyng at Midnight, or Cocke crowe, long Matyns, and Euenſonges, and other
ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Ceremonies, by the whiche, their bodies wer caſtigate, &amp; tor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mented many waies, with
harde beddes, and litle time reſtyng in them, wearyng heire clothe, next their ſkynnes, yron
aboute their middle, beatyng themſelfes ofte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tymes, with whippes, &amp; ſcorges and ſuffre
other, to ſcorge theim with whippes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei might ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fre
<pb facs="tcp:4757:102"/> pein in their bodies, that by that meanes, thei might deſerue heauen, and be
worthie, the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry eternall: but by that meanes, thei could not come to eternall glory, with God
the father, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che requireth none ſuche thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, at their handes, to come to heauen: But GOD
requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, that thei ſhould bee follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers of Chriſte, and ſuffre paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently affliccions,
that God ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to them, or chaunce to them in the worlde, and to haue a ſure faith, and
truſt in Gods mercie, grace, and fauor, and onely by the mercie of GOD, to come to ſaluacion,
for Chriſtes ſake one<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, and not for their awne woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, deedes, or merites, or other their
puniſhmentes, had in their bodies, by the which, thei obtein
<pb facs="tcp:4757:102"/> no iuſtice, holines, nor perfeccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before God y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faither, although, parauenture
before the worlde, thei were cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pted holy, for thoſe thynges. But what haue theſe
pſeudoapoſtles, obteined before God? Any iuſtice, holines, God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines, by their
ſuperſticion, fey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned humblenes, and by muche maceracio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their bodies? Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely no holines,
nor iuſtice with God, nor yet no honor in Gods ſight, but rather diſhonor, ſinne, and
wickednes, for thei haue ſoughte holines, where no holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes was to be gotten, as of mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,
drynkes, holy daies, Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, of mennes Tradicions, phantaſies, and inuencions, of chaſtyng
the body, out of mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, contrary to Gods lawe, for thei do not geue the body, ſuche
<pb facs="tcp:4757:103"/> moderate ſuſtenaunce, as was neceſſary for it, to preſerue it in health,
to ſerue the ſpirit of God and to bryng furthe, the workes of the ſpirite.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The .iii. Chapiter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Herefore if you haue ryſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with Chryſte, ſeke thoſe thynges that are aboue, where
Chriſte is ſittyng, on the right hande of GOD. Care for thoſe thynges, that are aboue, and
not vpon yearthly thynges. For you be ded, and your life hid with Chriſte in God: when Chriſte
ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:4757:103"/> be ſhewed your life, then you with hym, ſhalbe ſhe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wed in glorie:</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle exhorteth theſe Coloſſians, and in them, al chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, to all holines,
and Godly conuerſacion of life, and that of the reſurreccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Chriſt, willing all men to
dye with Chriſte, &amp; to ariſe with Chriſt. As Chriſt died once, he dieth no more, ſo
ſhould al men die, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all ſyn, &amp; no more to returne again to ſinne. To a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe with
Chriſt, is to ariſe from ſyn, by true penance, &amp; to walke in a new life: a new life,
knoweth no old ſinnes, no carnall affecci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, no woorkes of darkenes, it abhorreth hypocryſy,
and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticion, and all Idolatrie, all fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie luſtes, deſires, or pleaſures,
<pb facs="tcp:4757:104"/> it doth ſeke iuſtice, not of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe nor of the workes of the law, nor of
ceremonies, or Tradicions of menne, of mannes Religion, nor yet in theſe thynges, putteth any
holines, or iuſtice, nor thynketh not Goddes honor or worſhip, to ſtande in outwarde thynges,
but GOD to bee a ſpirite, and would be worſhipped in ſpirite, and in truthe, by true faithe
in Chriſt, and not only with a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe, appoynted to worſhippe God, of man, &amp; not of
god alone.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Seke thoſe thynges, whiche are aboue, where Chriſte is ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng, at the right hand
of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.) If you be riſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with Chriſt it is youre duetie, not to ſeeke yearthly
thynges, as worldely honors, and promocions, digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, or worldly riches, but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue
<pb facs="tcp:4757:104"/> all theſe thynges, to ſeeke thoſe thynges that are aboue, that is, the
heauenly ioye, and bliſſe, life, and eternall felicitie, and the waies to come to theim, that
is, by true faithe in God, by ſure hope, and perfite Charitie, and by other Godly workes,
ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted of God, to be doen of al the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that ſhall come to that place where as Chriſte is
ſittyng, on the right hande of God the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to certifie vs, that all thei, whiche ſhall
ariſe with him, ſhal come to y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> place, where as Chriſt is, and that by Chriſte onely.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Seke heauenly thynges, and not yerthly thynges.) That thei ſhould more earneſtly,
ſette their mindes, vpon heauenly thinges more then vpon thoſe thynges, that are vpon the
yearth, or par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tein
<pb facs="tcp:4757:105"/> to this preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t life, by yearth<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly thynges, he vnderſtandeth all the lawe,
workes of the lawe, as Circumciſion, Sacrifices, Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, diuerſties of meates, daies,
apparell, and all the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of the lawe, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pein of death, to bee kepte, whiche
thing, ſainct Paule doth not admit. Finally, by yearthly thynges, he vnderſtandeth all thynges,
in this preſent life, that plucketh mennes hartes &amp; myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, from God, and maketh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to
ſet more by them, then by God or by his worde, or by heauenly ioye, and the waie to come to the
heauenly ioye.</p>
            <p n="4">4 For you bee dedde, and your life hid with Chriſte.) Nowe he ſheweth the cauſe, why
they ſhould ſeke thynges aboue, and
<pb facs="tcp:4757:105"/> not beneth, or yearthly thynges, for thei are ded from yearthly thynges, that thei
ſhould liue to Chriſt, by true faithe, and God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conuerſacion of liuyng, for their lifes are
hid in Chriſt, and with Chriſte ſhall appere, when he ſhall come in greate glorie,
companied with all the holy an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelles of heauen, to iudge the quicke and the ded. Therfore in
Chriſte, let all our truſte be put, and deſire of hym onely, healthe, life, and ſaluacion.
And if any ſhould moue you, to deſpaire of the life to come with Chriſte, for affliccions, or
aduerſitie, that ſhould chaunce to you in this life, remembre that your life, is hid in
Chriſte, and doth not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere, to bee called a life, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a miſery, bothe for the
ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenes
<pb facs="tcp:4757:106"/> of it, and alſo for the tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitorie pleaſure of it, but then it ſhalbee
ſhewed, in the glorious co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming of Chriſt, as a rightous iudge, both of quick &amp; ded. Now ye
ſe that the life of the faithfull is hid here in Chriſt, and is kept by humblenes of the
Croſſe, as the faithfull had no life, but in the laſt daie, it ſhalbe ſhewed, to be a
ioyfull and bleſſed life, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che nowe appereth not bleſſed. This place maketh men ſure,
of the life to come in another world whiche, carnall and worldly me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, thynketh not of, nor yet
beleueth to come, and it moueth men, to haue ſure faithe, and conſtaunt hope in Chriſte, and
of the glory to come in Chriſt, and by Chriſt. Alſo it teacheth the life, of faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full men
to appere, here in this
<pb facs="tcp:4757:106"/> worlde, to be nothyng leſſe then a life, ye, good menne dooth here appere, as
thei were vtterly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken of God, and abiectes of al menne, and yet God hath reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued for
theim, a glorious life in the worlde to come, &amp; for hope of that life, here all aduerſities,
are to be borne paciently.</p>
            <p>Therfore, mortify your members, whiche are v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the yerth, as whordo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vncle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes, vnnatural
luſt euill concupiſcence, and coueteouſnes, whiche is the worſhippe of Idols, for the
whiche, the ire of God is wont to come, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al vntractable childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:4757:107"/> emonges who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, you wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ſome tyme, when you liued emonges them.</p>
            <p>Now he moueth theim, to kill and mortifie, all vice and ſynne, that vertues might bee ſette
in their places: and firſt, he willeth theim, to mortifie their yearthly members, that is, all
the workes of the fleſhe, whiche be reherſed. <hi>Gala. v.</hi> Worthy to bee eſchewed for
thei exclude menne from life, and bryngeth death to the doers excepte thei repent, and call to God,
for mercie and grace. And firſt, he willeth men to put away whoredome, aduoutrye, fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion,
and all vnclennes of the body, for theſe vices diſpleaſe God, prouoketh God to powre, his Ire
and Vengeaunce vpon
<pb facs="tcp:4757:107"/> men, and vpon the world. <hi>Gene. vi. Ephe. v.</hi> Thei kill the body, bryng to it
many incurable ſic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenes and diſeaſes, &amp; thei bryng ſhame to men in the world,
loſſe of goodes, riches, &amp; inheritaunce ofte tymes death of the body, by whores, and
finally, thei ſhutte out men from heauen. Theſe vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are mortified or killed, when we
forſake theim, and flee theim, and al occaſions of them, be put awaie from vs, and wee geue no
place to them, nor yet to no occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of theim, but that we morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie theim, by litle and litle,
by the workyng of the ſpirite of God, whiche maketh that ſynnes, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though thei be in vs, and
we can not be without theim <hi>.i. Iho. i.</hi> Yet thei reigne not in vs, nor we bee not obedient
to the deſires of
<pb facs="tcp:4757:108"/> ſynne, and that not of our ſelfes, but by the ſpirite of God. But what thyng
ſhall moue men, to forſake ſynne, and mortifie the deſires of ſyn? Surely nothyng more
moueth, to abhorre ſynne, then the remembraunce, how fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy a thyng ſynne is, how it
diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſeth almightie God, what ſhame, confuſion, &amp; pein, ſorowe, and woo
euerlaſtyng, it bryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth with it, howe it deſtroyeth, both body and ſoule, what ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geaunce
of God it prouoketh, to be powred vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole world: for God is the God, that willeth no ſynne
to be doen, nor will ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fre no ſynners, to dwel with him in his tabernacle. Again, to
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, what ioy, what bliſſe, &amp; what eternall felicitie, commeth to them, that killeth
all ſynne in
<pb facs="tcp:4757:108"/> them and abhorreth it, and ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dieth to liue Godly, in all good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. Synnes are to
be mortified firſte, by true penitence, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentaunce for ſynne, forſakyng ſynne, and
abhorryng it, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer intendyng to returne again to ſyn. Secondly, by true faithe in God the
father, truſtyng ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in his mercie and grace, that he will forgeue hym his ſynnes, not
for his deedes, woorkes, or merites, but onely for Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus ſake. Thirdly, by walkyng
vnfeinedly, in a newe life. Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redome is here rekened, firſte, to be mortified, becauſe it is
moſte daungerous, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vice, hihgeſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoketh God to powre his ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geaunce vpon men, becauſe
men oft tymes eſtemeth it, as leaſt of all ſynnes, and yet moſte of all
<pb facs="tcp:4757:109"/> ſynnes, it ſoneſt killeth both bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and ſoule, &amp; ſhutteth out men
from heauen. <hi>i. Corin. vi. Gala. v.</hi> And God will puniſhe fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, and adulterers,
<hi>Hebre. xii.</hi> So he will that al maner of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoutery, and fornicacion, ſhould be clerely
put awaie, and all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions of them. He willeth alſo that men ſhould mortifie, all
co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueteouſnes, and all vnſaciable deſire of money, of worldly ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and goodes, &amp;
would not that any ſhould loue money, more then GOD, nor make his God of his money, as the
coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous man doth, ſettyng all his mind and harte, vpon the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of the worlde, louyng
theim better then God, takyng more pein, to gette the gooddes of the worlde, then the true knowlege

<pb facs="tcp:4757:109"/> of God, and of his holy woorde, rather forſakyng God, then his riches, and more
ſory, for loſſe of worldly riches, then for loſſe of God. Suche coueteous men,
vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>merciful, ſhal not poſſeſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of heauen, for thei loue dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenes, better
then light, and ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore thei ſhall goo to darkenes, and to euerlaſtyng pein.</p>
            <p n="2">2 For the whiche, commeth the vengeaunce of God, vpon al in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractable children.) Marke
here for what thynges, commeth the vengeaunce of God vpon men, not for white meate eate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Lent
ſeaſon, or for egges eaten vpon the Fridaie, but for fornicacion, aduoutery, vnclennes, euill
lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes, and concupiſcences, couete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, and ſuch like, forbidden by Goddes lawe, whiche
prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
<pb facs="tcp:4757:110"/> the Ire God, and his ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geaunce. Learne that pein fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth ſynne, that none
thynke, that thei may lawfully ſynne, or that thei ſhall eſcape vnpuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed for ſynnes,
for God loueth no ſynne. <hi>Pſalme .v.</hi> And he will not ſuffre ſyn to be
vnpuniſhed.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Emonges whom you walked when you liued emonges them.) He ſheweth that theſe
Coloſſia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s was poluted with thoſe greate vices; ſome time when thei liued as Heathen
Gentiles, knowyng nothyng of God, but nowe thei are waſſhed, and purged from their ſynnes, by
Chriſte alone, and not by their workes, deedes or merites. Here we maie learne thoſe that was
ſome tyme euill, and filthy ſynners, nowe to bee good and iuſt men, to conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pne
<pb facs="tcp:4757:110"/> the olde ſaiyng: once euill &amp; euer euil, for if y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſaying ſhould be
al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies true, none of vs al ſhould be good, for we wer al once euil, by nature we are the
children, of the Ire and wrathe of God, and the children of darknes, now by Chriſte, we are made
the welbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued children of God, through his mercie and grace, for Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes ſake alone.</p>
            <p>Now truly put awaie all ire, indignacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, malice euil ſpeakyng, filthy ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng from your
mouth, lie not one to another, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that you haue put of, the old man with his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, and haue
putte on a newe man, whiche is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed
<pb facs="tcp:4757:111"/> to knowlege, and his Image whiche hath made hym, where as is no Gentile or Iewe,
Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, or vncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Barbarous or Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thian, bonde or free man, but all in all is
Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Here the Apoſtle moueth men to put awaie al ſinnes, that ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue may be ſette in their
places. And firſt, he willeth all ire, indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnacion, malice, rancor, enuie, ſlaunderyng of
other, filthy ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng to clerely to bee baniſhed, from me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes mouthes &amp;, that no
communicacion, ſhould be had emonges men, but ſuche as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth ſainctes. <hi>Eph. v.</hi>
That GOD might bee glorified, and
<pb facs="tcp:4757:111"/> other edified.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Lie not one to another.) Here is forbidden all liyng, craft, falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hed, or deceipte, in
byyng and ſellyng, in the whiche, is vſed muche craft and deceipt, and v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of ſo many,
and ſo ofte, as it wer a lawfull thyng, and not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Gods law, one to deceiue another, in
byyng and ſellyng. It is no ſmall vice, that bryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth men to hell, and to death: liyng,
crafte, and deceipte, bryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth to death. Therfore, thei are to bee eſchewed, and fledde of all
chriſtians, how ſo euer proffita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thei bee, or appere to bee to men. And this thyng, is
greatly to bee lamented, emonges Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, that after ſuch knowlege of Goddes truthe, had
emonges vs, that ſo many haue delight in
<pb facs="tcp:4757:112"/> liyng, in crafte, and falſhed, for lucre ſake, ye, this is more to bee lamented,
that ſuche euil men be not aſhamed, to confirme their lye, craft, or falſhed, with an oth,
callyng God to witnes, of their lyes, crafte, or falſhed.</p>
            <p n="3">3 After that you haue putte of, the olde man with his deedes.) Now he ſheweth the
cauſe, why thei ſhould eſchewe ſynne &amp; vice becauſe thei haue put of, the old man,
withal his concupiſcences, luſtes, and deſires, by true faith in Chriſt, that thei ſhould
walke no more, after the old man, &amp; his affeccions, but that thei ſhould, put one a newe man,
that is, the ſpirite of God, and walke after hym, and bryng furthe the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of the ſpirite,
euery daie by all their life tyme, hauyng their
<pb facs="tcp:4757:112"/> hartes and myndes, ruled by the ſame ſpirite.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Whiche is renewed to know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege, and to the Image of God, that hath made hym.) Here is
ſhewed, how we ſhall put on the newe manne, and be renewed in hym, it muſte be by knowlege of
GOD the father, whiche, hath made vs, like to his Image. <hi>Gene. ii.</hi> Whiche regardeth not
perſons, nor careth not whether, he be a Iewe or a Gentile, Scot or an Engliſheman, ſeruaunt
or Maſter, a man or a woman, but Chriſt is all in all thynges, that is, he that hath Chriſte,
hath all thynges, as all holines, iuſtice, and righteouſnes. If the newe man bee put on, by
knowlege of God, whom put thei on, whiche knowe not God, nor his worde?
<pb facs="tcp:4757:113"/> If men be renewed in the ſpirite of God, by knowlege of God, in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are thei
renewed, that kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth not God? But in the ſpirit of the deuil, how can thei folowe Chriſt, and
do his commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, that know not God, nor yet his will by his worde? Gods will and
pleaſure, is knowen by his worde, therefore, learne how neceſſary a thyng it is, to knowe God
by his worde, for the ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of manne conſiſteth, in this true knowlege of God. <hi>Iho.
xvii.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Put you on as elect of God, holy and welbelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, the bowels of mercy ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tlenes, modeſtnes,
me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenes, ſoftnes, ſufferyng one another, and mutual
<pb facs="tcp:4757:113"/> forgeuing one another, if you haue any co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaint a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt any, &amp; as chriſt
hath forgeuen you, ſo doo you.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle moueth theſe Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſſians, and in them all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, to haue the ſame
vertues, that the electe of God to eternall ſaluacion hath, and in theim to walke, and increaſe
euery daie, more and more, &amp; theſe vertues ſheweth to vs, who be elected of God, and who
not, as farre as manne can iudge, by outwarde thynges. The elected of God, to euerlaſtyng ioye
and bliſſe, thei fle and hate all vice and ſynne, thei loue vertue, and Godly li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng, and in
it do walke, al their life tyme, by true faith, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of the ſpirite.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb facs="tcp:4757:114"/>2 Bowelles of mercie, gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.) He ſheweth what vertues, the elected of God
ſhould putte on: he willeth them to put on, the bowelles of mercie, that is, that thei ſhould
haue like pitie and compaſſion, as hath mothers, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes their children. The in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward partes
of mothers, be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to helpe, when thei here or ſe their children, wante neceſſaries, and
thei wil helpe their children to their powers: ſo ſhould euery one of vs, be affected one to
ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as the mother to her childe. This place reproueth all cruell menne, that be vnmercifull,
that care not for other, ſo thei be well themſelfes, and liue in all welth and pleaſure.
Alſo he willeth that thei ſhouldbe gentle, meke, modeſt, ſober, deſcrete, ſoft,
hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,
<pb facs="tcp:4757:114"/> and lowly to all menne: and here is rebuked ſtubburne, ſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, froward,
ouerthwarte, cruell, and all froward maners.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Sufferyng one another.) He moueth theim, to ſuffre all iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and wronges
paciently, and one to beare with another, and readie to forgeue diſpleaſures and iniuries dooen
one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and not to geue checke for checke, or taunt for taunt, nor to auenge hymſelf of
iniuries, but to forgeue, and to prate for them that do vs iniury or wrong, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the example of
Chriſt: but of theſe thynges, more largely is ſpoken. <hi>Ephe. iiii.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Aboue al thinges haue Charitie, whiche is the bonde of perfeccion, and
<pb facs="tcp:4757:115"/> the peace of God, maie triumph in your hartes, in the which you are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in one
body, and bee you thankefull.</p>
            <p>Emonges all vertues, Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie excelleth, for it is the bond of all perfeccion, and knitteth all
vertues together, &amp; by the which Chriſtians bee knit together, by ſuche a bonde of
charitie, as can neuer bee loſed: for as membres bee knit in the body, by ioyntes, ſo
Chriſtians by Charitie, and one cannot be ſeparated from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, for it byndeth members of
Chriſte together, and it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth perfite the whole body. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain of the contrary, ire, hatered
enuie, debate, ſtrief, and conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, plucketh the body in peces
<pb facs="tcp:4757:115"/> where as by Charitie, all mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers are made perfite.</p>
            <p n="2">2 And the peace of God, maie triumphe and haue vyctory in youre bodies.) That is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peace
of God, maie ouercome in you, al ire &amp; enuie, hatred or malice, iniury or wronges, and let hym
thynke he hath victorie, that is, in peace with his enemies, and aduerſaries, that hath doen him
iniurie or wrong, not deſiryng any vengeau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of him, but prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng to God, that he maie repent,
and amend his naughtie life, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittyng all iniuries frely, from his harte: and this is the peace,
not of this world, nor of the fleſh but it is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peace of God, whiche God worketh in peaceable
men, whiche ſhalbe called the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of GOD. <hi>Math. v.</hi> And to this
<pb facs="tcp:4757:116"/> peace we bee called of God, that we ſhould thinke al one thing, &amp; that after
Ieſus Chriſte, &amp; that wee ſhould bee one, thankefull, kynde, and louyng to another.</p>
            <p>The worde of GOD maie dwell in you abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dauntly, with al wiſedo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Teache and moniſh one
another, with ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges and praiſynges, and ſpiritual Pſalmes, with thankes, ſyngyng in
youre hartes to the Lorde. And what ſoeuer you ſhall dooe, in worde or in deede, do all thynges
in the name of our Lorde Ieſu, geuyng thankes to God, and the
<pb facs="tcp:4757:116"/> father by hym.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle moueth theim, that thei ſhould receiue the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of God, and that it
ſhould not, onely of theim bee learned, but alſo, that it ſhould dwell in them abundauntly,
and be ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fixed in harte and memorie, &amp; that one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſhould teach ano<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther. And
here <hi>Lyra</hi> ſaieth, that it is required of vs, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhould haue all vnderſtandyng of
holy ſcriptures. <hi>Gloſa interlinia.</hi> But how or when, will thei haue the vnderſtandyng
of holy ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, that will not rede holy ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, nor yet here them red, or ſkarſe
can ſuffre, that other rede holy ſcriptures. This place re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proueth theim, that would not haue
laye men, to rede holy ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, that thei might vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande
<pb facs="tcp:4757:117"/> them: If it be not lawfull for laye menne, to rede the holy ſcriptures, nor yet to
ſtudy them when ſhall the worde of GOD, dwel in them abundauntly? For the true knowlege of
ſcripture, is gotten by readyng, ſtudiyng, hearyng the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> rede and declared: and here he
ſpeaketh, aſwell to laye menne, as to prieſtes, for he would haue all menne perfite, in the
knowlege of the truthe, that thei might liue after the truth.</p>
            <p n="2">2 In all wiſedo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, teachyng and moniſhyng the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelfes and other, in all wiſedom,
neceſſary for ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uacion. Here note what dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce the Apoſtle requireth, that one ſhould
teach another, in the true wiſedome, and euery one accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng to his vocacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, with great
reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, honor, and Godly feare
<pb facs="tcp:4757:117"/> The worde of God is to bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated, &amp; handeled, with greate wiſedome and
ſobernes, and not raſhly, fooliſhly, boldly, or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcretly, and therfore, he addeth with
all wiſedom, bothe of God and of man: the woorde of God ſeyng it is holy, and ſheweth vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to
vs, the eternall will of GOD it requireth a man, all dedicated to God, whiche maie vſe ofte
ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, feruent praier to God, and the whiche hath the feare of god before his iyes alwaie, willyng
at no time to do that thyng, that ſhould diſpleaſe God, in woorde or in deede. Twoo thynges
the apoſtle requireth of vs, doctrine and monicion, but there be ſome that bee called and
appoynted, and thei openly maie teache, and moniſhe, exhorte in publique co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregacions
<pb facs="tcp:4757:118"/> of men. Other there bee, that bee not openly called to be preachers or teachers,
&amp; thei priuatly may teache, and admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhe, and ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly in their priuate houſes, to their
wife, childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and ſeruauntes.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Teache and admoniſhe, one another.) Thoſe thynges ſaieth S. Ambroſe, ſhould be
taught, whiche ſounde Chriſte, whiche ſmell Chriſte, and ſetteth furthe his glory and
doctryne, and this not onely ſung or ſaid by mouth but alſo in the harte, with a fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent
zeale to GOD, and that in ſonges, praiſynges, and in ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall hymnes, with thankes ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng
to God, for his benefites. But how ſhould laye men, ſyng ſpirituall ſonges, laudes,
Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, and Hymnes, to GOD in
<pb facs="tcp:4757:118"/> their hartes, excepte thei ſhould learne them, or rede the holy ſcri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ptures,
theimſelfes? This place ſheweth, that it is lawful for lay men, to rede holy ſcriptures, and
to learne, that thei might reherſe ſpiritual ſonges, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thei worke vpon their handie
labors: and it conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pneth all them, that thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth it is not lawfull, for laye men and laie women,
to rede ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſcriptures, and haue theim by hart, that thei might ſyng, laude praiſe, and
thankes to God.</p>
            <p n="4">4 What ſoeuer you do, in word or in deede, do all thynges in the name of our lorde
Ieſus.) Now is declared for what end, ſhould all our woordes and deedes bee dooen, that thei
muſte be for the glory of God, that the name of God, might bee glorified in all
<pb facs="tcp:4757:119"/> men, and thankes geuen to God for his benefites. This place re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proueth all
hypocrytes, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblers, that ſeketh their awne glorye, more then the glorye of God,
that ſtudy to pleaſe menne more then God.</p>
            <p>You wiues obeye your awne huſbandes, as it is mete in the Lorde. You me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> loue your wifes, and
be not bitter again to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
            </p>
            <p>Of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mutuall duetie betwene man and his wife, I haue ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at large. <hi>Ephe. v.</hi> What
bee the cauſes of Godly Matrimonie, and what is the duetie, of either of them, to the other. Now
ſainct Paule ſaieth, it is the office or duetie of the wife, what eſtate or degree ſo euer
ſhe bee, to be obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient
<pb facs="tcp:4757:119"/> to her huſband, in al law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and honeſt cauſes, and that willyngly and
gladly, ſtudiyng alwaie to pleaſe hym, in the lord withoute all murmuryng, or grudging
againſt him, and that for the ordinaunce of God, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che hath ordeined, that wifes ſhould be
obedient to their huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, whatſoeuer thei be, poore or riche, noble or vnnoble. If a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
would thynke to be Maſter, ouer their huſbandes, by reaſon of their noble ſtocke and kynred
of their riches, landes, or poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, let them knowe that Gods lawe and ordinaunces,
byndeth theim to obedience to their huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandes, and he that reſiſteth the ordinaunce of God,
taketh vnto hymſelf iudgement. <hi>Roma. xiii.</hi> Therefore, let euery one beware
<pb facs="tcp:4757:120"/> that thei breake not Goddes or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, for thei that breake his ordinaunce, thei
ſhall not eſcape vnpuniſhed, if thei here in this worlde do not repent, and cal to God for
mercie, and forgeuenes of their ſynnes, in true faithe.</p>
            <p n="2">2 You menne, loue your wifes, and bee not bitter in ire againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.) The duetie of the
huſband is to loue his wife, as his awne body, and as Chriſt hath loued vs: then no man
ſhould hate his wife, for he hateth not his awne body, not to haſtie, angry, or checke, or
bitter in woordes, or deedes, or dooe that thyng, that ſhould iuſtly anger, or diſpleaſe
her, and to ouer ſe, and wynke at many fautes in his wife, &amp; ſtudy with gentlenes to
reforme, that he proueth to be amiſſe, for ſo he
<pb facs="tcp:4757:120"/> would his wife ſhould dooe to hym, and ſo to beare the infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the
weaker veſſels, &amp; not to be churliſhe, frowarde, ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thwarte, or with bitter woordes,
ſoundyng to the diſhoneſtie of his wife, and of hymſelf, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke his wife to anger, to
greue or vexe her, or otherwiſe to dooe not his duetie to her, to put her awaie, and take an
whore, and vſe company with a drabbe, and a harlot, contrary to Gods lawe and will, whiche thyng
God wil not ſuffre, long vnpuniſhed, bee thei neuer ſo ſtoute, or hye in the world. But of
the duetie of man and wife, one to another, I haue babled very largely, accordyng to Gods woorde.
<hi>Ephe. v.</hi> as I truſte, and therefore I paſſe it lightly, here in this place.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:4757:121"/>Children, obeye youre fathers and mothers, in all thinges, this pleaſeth God.
Fathers, diſcorage not your children, not to muche, leaſt thei be ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and can geue you
no anſwere for feare.</p>
            <p>He teacheth the duetie of chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to their parentes, and again of parentes, that is of
fathers &amp; mothers, to their childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. It per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teineth to childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to be humble, lowly, gentle,
and obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and mothers, in all thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges lawfull and honeſt, and in all thynges,
that be not contrary to Goddes law, and in nowiſe to reſiſt, to ſpeake again the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, except
pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes require vnlawful thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,
<pb facs="tcp:4757:121"/> it is the duetie of children, to honor their fathers and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, to help,
ſuccour them, and releue theim, if thei maie better then father or mother, when any occaſion
ſhalbee geuen to their children, to be an helper and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter, to their fathers and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers:
and this thyng pleaſeth God better, then al pilgrimages makyng, giltyng of Images: ye better then
all the Biſhoppe of Romes liyng Pardons, for this is the commaundement of God, the other bee not
of God, but of members of Goddes aduerſary, that is, of the deuill.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Fathers, diſcorage not youre childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to muche.) It is the due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of fathers &amp;
mothers, not to diſcorage their childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to muche or by their threatenyng wordes,
<pb facs="tcp:4757:122"/> beatyng, bunchyng, knockyng vpon them, to dawe their childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and to make theim dawe
pates, ſo fearfull and amaſed, that thei dare not ſpeake a woorde, nor geue a right
anſwere, and all for feare of their parentes, to fearſe ouer their children. For as to muche
pamperyng &amp; cheriſhyng of parentes, bee the deſtruccion to their children, ſo bee
deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion to children, to muche fearſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes of parentes, to their childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: therefore fathers
and mothers, muſt vſe a moderate meane, not to fearſe, nor yet to ſofte, but if their
children do offende theim, or do a faute, let them be correc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with admonicions, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes
of rewardes, if thei will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mende, and faute no more, for if children ſhould not be corrected
<pb facs="tcp:4757:122"/> for their fautes, thei would be to wanton, to ſhrode, curſſed, and vnhappie,
and full of all euill, therefore it is true, that Sala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſaieth. <hi>Qui parcit uirge odit
filium.</hi> He that ſpareth the rod, hateth the child. And the Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophier ſaith, that an
euil, in the beginnyng, maie ſone bee reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died, but if it haue long conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued, oft tymes it is
vncurable: therefore, reſiſt an euil at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnyng of it, and ſo it maie the ſoner be
healed, but of theſe due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, that is, of the parentes to their children, and of children to
their parentes, I haue ſhewed my mynde more largely, in the Commentarie to the Epheſia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s.
<hi>Ephe. vi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seruauntes obey by al
<pb facs="tcp:4757:123"/> thynges, them which are Maſters after the fleſhe, not with ſeruice, lowely
before their iyes, as you ſtudie to pleaſe men, but with ſimplenes of harte, fearyng God. And
what ſoeuer you ſhall do, do it of an hartines, as you ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued God and not manne, knowyng
that you ſhall receiue of God, a reward of inheritaunce, for you ſerue our Lorde Chriſte.
Furthermore, he that hath ſynned, ſhall beare his ſynne, and there is no
<pb facs="tcp:4757:123"/> reſpect of perſones before God. Maſters geue equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and equalnes, to your
ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, knowing that you haue a Lorde in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</p>
            <p>In the former parte of this texte is taught, the duetie of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes, to their Maſters,
who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thei ſerue in this life, whom thei ſerue, whether it bee for meate, drynke, apparell, and
wages, or for thoſe, &amp; for learnyng, of ſome honeſt ſcience, or for other
neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary cauſes: And in this latter part is declared, thoffice of Ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſters, to their
ſeruauntes. The duetie of ſeruauntes is, to obeye their Maſters, in all lawful, and honeſt
thynges, to vſe them low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:4757:124"/> and mekely, to their Maſters and to haue their Maſters in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence, with all
diligent ſeruice ſtudie to pleaſe theim, not onely in their iye ſight, with faithfull,
truſtie, and profitable ſeruice, ſtudie to pleaſe their Maſters, but alſo in their
abſence, &amp; when their Maſters, dooe not ouer ſee them. This place reproueth ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
negligent ſeruauntes, which will bee faithfull, iuſte, true, and dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, in their Maſters
labors and buſines, as long as their Maſter is preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and doth loke on them: but if their
Maſters be abſent, or awaie from theim, or do not ouer ſe them, thei care not how litle worke
thei do, thei care not, who dooe more then thei, ye, thei will bee pickyng, and ſtea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng, and
liyng, all ſuche be here
<pb facs="tcp:4757:124"/> reproued by the holy ghoſt, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kyng here in ſaincte Paule, and <hi>Ephe.
vi.</hi> More at large: ſuche negligente ſeruauntes, deceiue not onely their Maſters, but
al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo theimſelfes, for thei diſpleaſe GOD highly, for ſeruauntes ſhould ſerue their
Maſters here in this worlde, as faithfully, iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtely, and truely, as if thei ſerued God, for
in deede thei ſerue God that ſerue their Maſters, as here is commaunded, that is, to ſerue
theim, in all veritie, and truthe, faithfulnes, and iuſtice, with all diligence, in all humblenes
of harte, and mynd, in woorde and deede, fearyng GOD, and their Maſters, dooyng alwaie their
Maſters buſines, to the mooſte profite &amp; pleaſure, of their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter in GOD, knowyng
ſurely
<pb facs="tcp:4757:125"/> that thei ſo doyng, ſerue GOD and if thei dooe not ſo, that thei diſpleaſe
God, when thei do not their buſines, as thei ſhould do, but parauenture will murmure and
grudge, to dooe that their Maſter commaundeth theim, or will geue hym again a froward anſwere,
and make ouerthwarte wordes, froward and ſtubburne or when thei go from their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, with a
dogs pater noſter, murmuryng with theimſelfes, I cannot tell what, againſt their Maſter,
patteryng, thynkyng their Maſter, to put the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to great peines &amp; labors, ſuche euill
ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes there be with other, that will picke, ſteale, and lye, &amp; haue many naughtie
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dicions, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, all are to be amended in ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes, that ſeruauntes might
<pb facs="tcp:4757:125"/> ſerue and pleaſe GOD, doyng their Maſters lawful commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dementes, and receiue
of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reward, better then any gold or ſiluer, landes, or poſſeſſions, life eternal:
Whiche God geueth as well to ſeruauntes, as Maſters without reſpecte of perſones.</p>
            <p n="2">2 For you ſerue youre Lorde God.) This thyng ſhould make all ſeruauntes, to thynke
all la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors or peines, that thei bee put to in their Maſters ſeruice, to be eaſy, that thei
ſeruyng their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and doyng with al gladnes and faithful dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters
commaundement, that thei ſerue God, the father of our lord Ieſu Chriſte, what tyme ſoeuer
it bee, by daie or by nighte. And who ſhould bee werie, in the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of God: this is his
true ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice:
<pb facs="tcp:4757:126"/> as for the other ſeruice of God (called Goddes ſeruice, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſed by manne, let
other iudge whether it be Goddes ſeruice or no) this I am ſure, that the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunte, occupied
faithfully and iuſtely, is occupied in Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice: And again, thei that do not their
Maſters lawful commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, ſhall be puniſhed of God whiche, both rewardeth and
pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth, without reſpecte of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſone. Let euery ſeruaunt, do his duetie to his
Maſter, and ſo is God pleaſed.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Maſters, do you equitie and al equalnes to your ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes.) You Maſters, doo your
dueties to your ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, let them haue ſufficient meate and drynke, and other
neceſſaries, let them not be idle, but ſet theim to ſome honeſt
<pb facs="tcp:4757:126"/> woorkes, laye not to muche lode vpon their backes, more then thei are able to beare,
remember that thei with you, ſhalbee felo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes in the heauenly inheritau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce Se more if you
pleaſe. <hi>Ephe. vi.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The .iiij. Chapiter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>E inſtaunt in prayer, watche in it, with ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes, pray alſo for vs, that GOD
might open to vs, the doore of his woorde, that wee mighte ſpeake the miſterie of Chriſt, for
the whiche I am bound,
<pb facs="tcp:4757:127"/> that I might ſhewe it as it beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth me to ſpeke.</p>
            <p>Of praier, he hath ſpoken of before in the firſt Chapiter, how thei ſhould praie, to whom
thei ſhould praie, what thei ſhould deſire in their praiers, &amp; of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and for whoſe
ſake, thei ſhould be heard. Now he moueth theim to be conſtaunt in praier, and in theim vs
all, and to watche in praier, with geuyng of thankes to God, for his benefites, of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> commeth al
goodnes, and final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, he deſireth theim to praie for hym. This place moueth vs to praier, and to
be inſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer, and to praie oft tymes, with feruent mynde and hartie deſire, and that
wee ſhould deſire other to praie for vs, beyng a liue, as
<pb facs="tcp:4757:127"/> Paule here was, and it repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth our ſlothfulnes in praier, and ſuche as loue
to pray litle, &amp; will not other to praie for them, the praier of a iuſt man, is much worthe
with God, for it is harde if no impediment be in hym, for whom praier is made, or if it bee
deſired of GOD, accordyng to his will.</p>
            <p n="2">2 That God might open to vs the doore of his word. For what thyng he deſired theim, to
praye for hym, it is ſhewed, that God, ſhould open his mouthe, that he might ſpeake the
woorde, not of manne, but of God, as it did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come hym to ſpeake. Here wee learne twoo thynges,
the one is, that to ſpeake the worde of God as a manne ſhould doo it, is the gifte of God, and
not mannes
<pb facs="tcp:4757:128"/> will and pleaſure: the other, that it muſte be deſired of GOD, by faithful
praier, both of the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, and alſo of the auditors, and that no manne of his awne might and
powers, can ſpeake the worde of God, as he ſhould do, excepte that God ſhall firſte open
his mouthe, and geue hym grace to ſpeake, as he ſhould do, to the glory of God, and to the
profite of other.</p>
            <p n="3">3 For the whiche, I am bound.) Paule was in priſon, when he wrote this Epiſtle, to
theſe Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſſians, and he was not aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, to name his fetters &amp; bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, he was in,
whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he wrote this Epiſtle, for it was not for his awne ſake, but for the Goſpels ſake.
Theſe bee the ſwete delica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, that true preachers, and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<pb facs="tcp:4757:128"/> furthe of Gods holy worde ſhould looke for in this worlde, but in the world to
come, is eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall delicates prepared for them if thei ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſure, to the holy Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell of
GOD, and ſhrinke not from it, by no affliccion or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecucion.</p>
            <p>walke wiſely toward ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers, redemyng the tyme: youre communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, let it bee alwaie
fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourable, ſeaſoned with ſalt, that you maie know howe it behoueth you to anſwere to
euery man.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle geueth them mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicion, to walke as it beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth, towardes ſtraungiers, that is,
wiſely as it becommeth wiſeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<pb facs="tcp:4757:129"/> in God, in all truthe, iuſtice, and righteouſnes, not as vnwiſemen but as
wiſeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>Ephe. v.</hi> So that ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers, or foreiners, can haue no iuſte cauſe to
ſpeake euill of you, nor of your maners, rede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng the tyme, dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly ſekyng oportunitie, to
doo good to all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or if in tymes paſt, you haue been euill, now be no more euill, from
hencefurthe, ſtudiyng al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waie to profite other.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Let your communicacion, be alway with fauor, ſeaſoned with ſalt.) What their
wordes ſhould bee, here is ſhewed. Firſt, he wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, that their wordes ſhould be alwaie
with fauor, that be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunt, gentle, meke, and with ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brietie, that thei maie be thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
to the hearers, that ſetteth furth Goddes glory, promoteth
<pb facs="tcp:4757:129"/> his woorde, that bryng the loue and feare of GOD, and that be profitable, and
confortable in God, and in all goodnes, to the hearers. This place reproueth, all idle
ſpeakynges, and talkyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, of the whiche, commeth no profite to man, nor glory to God it
checketh vain ſpeakynges, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill ſpeakynges, and all ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynges, that tendeth to the hurt or
damage to other.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Let your wordes be ſeaſoned with ſalte) Salt was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to be had, in all
ſacrifice. <hi>Leui. ii.</hi> (By y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which, was ſignified hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly wiſedom.) Salt
ſeaſoneth all meates, it draweth out cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt bloud &amp; humors, it perceth to the bone, it is
a ſharpe eager thyng, gnawyng ſore. So muſt oure woordes bee ſeaſoned with
<pb facs="tcp:4757:130"/> ſalte, that is, ſpirituall wiſedom, that ſeaſoneth all thynges, and maketh
euery man ſauery, and good, willyng, &amp; glad, to pleaſe God, and to ſeke thoſe thynges,
that bryngeth to heauen, ſo it be commeth our wordes, to bee ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned, that thei maie
ſounde no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng els, but Godlines, Godly wiſedo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Godly honor, and glory the loue of GOD, the
feare of God, with geuyng thankes to God, for his benefites to vs, ſo our woordes ſhould alwaie
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, that we be Chriſtians, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to knowe Chriſt, and his doctryne, and to folowe
it in our liuyng, &amp; to moue other, by oure good example, bothe in woorde and deede, to bee
followers of Chriſte. This place reproueth, fooliſhe and vain wordes, raſhe
<pb facs="tcp:4757:130"/> talkyng, withour wiſedome, by the whiche, ofte tymes commeth muche hurte.</p>
            <p n="4">4 That you maie knowe, howe it becommeth you to anſwere to euery manne.) Now is
declared, what he meaneth by ſalte, ſurely nothyng els, but that he would haue men, to haue
that wiſedome that thei might knowe, how thei ſhould anſwere to euery manne, that their
wordes might be tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kefull and profitable: otherwiſe menne muſt anſwere to princes, then to
ſubiectes, that not one anſwere, is mete at all tymes, to the weake, and to the ſtrong in
faithe, the weake muſte be fedde with milke, the ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g with ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g meate, but alwaie lette
your an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere be, to the glory of GOD, and to the profit of other. Lerne
<pb facs="tcp:4757:131"/> that of holy ſcripture, whiche is ſignified by ſalte, you maie lerne all
wiſedome, how you ſhall an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere euery man, in al Godlines and goodnes.</p>
            <p>Of all thynges pertei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng to me Lychycus, ſhall certifie you of them our welbeloued brother,
and faithfull Miniſter, &amp; ſeruaunte in the Lorde, whom I haue ſent vnto you for this
purpoſe, that he might know how you do, and comfort you har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, and with hym One<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimus a
faithfull brother which is of you: of al thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges thei ſhall ſhewe you
<pb facs="tcp:4757:131"/> what are in doyng here.</p>
            <p>Paule co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendeth to theſe Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſſians, twoo menne: the one is Tichicus, thother is
Oneſimus whiche, ſome tyme was an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable ſeruaunt (for he ſtale his Maſters
goodes, and ranne awaie from his Maſter Phile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon) but now he is a profitable ſeruaunte, and a
brother in the Lorde, and a faithfull Miniſter vnto me. By theſe twoo as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pereth, Paule
ſent his Epiſtle to theſe Coloſſians, and he ſaieth, the Tychicus ſhould certifie
them of all thynges, perteinyng to his awne ſtate, &amp; why he was caſt in priſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and for
what cauſe, and how he was vſed in priſon. Alſo Tychicus doth come, that he might knowe
your actes and dedes, &amp; commend your workes
<pb facs="tcp:4757:132"/> and reproue, if any thyng bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe, and ſhewe you howe, you ſhould leue
euill doyng, and do well, and alſo that might co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort your hartes in God, in al good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and
truth: And as for One<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimus, ſome tyme an euill ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunt, to his Maſter Philemo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, it is
long ſence, that he was ſory for his offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and euerſence that tyme, he hath been a good
man, a faithfull ſeruaunt in Chriſt, a true Miniſter vnto me, in the Goſpell, and how
vnprofitable, ſoeuer he was before, now he is a profitable ſeruaunte, and will recompenſe,
all that was amiſſe dooen by hym. Learne here, that GOD is mercifull, to penitent ſynners,
and that he forgeueth their ſynnes, callyng in true faithe, for mercie to God. Alſo
<pb facs="tcp:4757:132"/> that the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon prouerbe is falſe that is, he that is once euill, is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer euill,
whiche ſaiyng is euill, and worthie reproche. For this Oneſimus was once euill, but now good:
So we all were once euill, but now by Chriſte, we bee made good. <hi>Rom. v.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ariſtarchus my felow (in priſon and bondes) ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luteth you, and Marcus the ſuſters
ſonne to Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas, of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you haue receiued commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, if he ſhall come vnto you,
receiue hym, and Ieſus whiche is called Iuſt, which are Iewes. Theſe onely be workers
<pb facs="tcp:4757:133"/> with me, to the kingdom of GOD, whiche haue been to my conforte.</p>
            <p>That remaineth of this Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, Paule occupieth it with ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutacions, and here he
ſaluteth theim, in the name of three ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, that was of Ariſtarchus (of whom it is
written. <hi>Actes .xix.</hi>) Of Marcus the ſuſters ſonne of Barnabas, and of Ieſus, and
theſe three, was of the Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, that is, of the Iewes, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che he commendeth aboue all
other, at this preſent tyme, bothe for the faithfulnes, in helpyng forwarde Goddes woorde, and
alſo for conforte to hym in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that thei viſited hym in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and alſo did geue
to hym all neceſſaries.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb facs="tcp:4757:133"/>2 Marcus the ſuſters ſonne of Barnabas, ſaluteth you.) He ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luteth them in
the name of Mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cus ſuſters ſonne to Barnabas, deſiryng the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to receiue hym gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely, with
al humilitie, into their company, and take hym as one, very welcome to theim. Behold, Paule did not
forgette his fren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, but commendeth theim to his fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, deſiryng kindenes to be ſhewed for
kyndenes, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefites doen in this worlde, and ſpecially he willeth, kyndenes and benefites to
bee ſhewed, to the faithfull preachers, and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters furthe of Goddes holy, and bleſſed
worde.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Onely theſe be workers with me, to the kyngdome of GOD, whiche haue been to my
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort.) Theſe three, Ariſtarchus, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus,
<pb facs="tcp:4757:134"/> and Ieſus, nothyng fearing the cruelnes of enemies to God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des woorde, did viſite
Paule in priſon, or was with hym priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, for the Goſpell, as Paule was: thei co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forted
Paule in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, thei helped hym, thei proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for hym neceſſaries, and ſo thei were
confortable to hym, and alſo woorkers with hym, to the kyngdom of God, that was, in promoting
Gods holy worde to the vttermoſt of their powers with all faithfulnes &amp; diligence. Marke howe
fewe did embrace the Goſpelll, and did ſticke to Paule in priſon, or to his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctryne, of the
whiche we gather, the aucthoritie and veritie of do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctryne, not to bee eſtemed of the multitude
of men, that beleue it, or openly without al feare of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:4757:134"/> or loſſe of gooddes, or fauor of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, do profeſſe it, for here Paule
ſpeaketh but of three that was workers, to the kyngdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God and yet Paules doctrine was of God,
and of eternall veritie.</p>
            <p>Epaphras ſaluteth you whiche is of you, a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunt of Chriſte, alwaie earneſtly
labouryng for you in praiers, that you maie ſtande perfite and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plete, full in al the will of
God. I beare record to hym, that he hath greate care for you, and for them that are at Laodice, and
for theim whiche are at Hierapole.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:4757:135"/>Paule goeth furthe, with his ſalutacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and now he ſaluteth theim, in the name
of Epaphras a priſoner with Paule, by whoſe labours and preachynges, theſe Coloſſians
heard the Goſpell, &amp; beleued it. This Ephaphras cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed not, to praie for theſe
Coloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians, that thei might be perfite, and filled in all the will of God, after true
knowlege. This Epa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phras ſheweth thoffice of a true paſtor, that it is his office to preache
the worde of God, pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly &amp; ſincerely to his flocke: Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, to pray to God earneſtly
for theim, that thei might ſtande ſure, againſt all aſſautes of the deuill, the worlde,
and the fleſhe, and that thei might be fulfilled, in all knowlege of the will of God, and doo it:
and as he was
<pb facs="tcp:4757:135"/> carefull for his flocke: ſo ſhould other paſtors bee carefull, for their
flockes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted to theim.</p>
            <p>Lucas a phiſicia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (dere<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly beloued) ſaluteth you, and Demas. Salute the brethren, which are
at Laodicia, and Nimpha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany that are in her houſe. And when this Epiſtle ſhalbe
reher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed of you, loke that it be redde in the Churche of Laodice, and that which is written from
Laodice loke that you reade it.</p>
            <p>Paule remembreth here Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cas, whiche was a continuall fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe
<pb facs="tcp:4757:136"/> with Paule, in all his Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimage, and progreſſe of his preachyng, and a
perpetuall fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe of his bondes, as Paule writeth. <hi>ii.. Timo. iiii.</hi> Where he ſaieth,
that Lucas is with me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone. Marke, that when all for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaked Paule, Lucas remained with hym
alone, that he ſhould be to vs, an example of conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and of ſure faithe, that wee
ſhould not forſake the faithe of Chriſte, for affliccions, priſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and bondes. This
Lucas is he, that wrote the Goſpel, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Goſpell of ſaincte Luke, and the Actes of the
Apoſtles. Learne here, what felowes and Miniſters Paule had, that wee maie know that it helpeth
much to true Godlines, &amp; to gett good maners, to haue company, with
<pb facs="tcp:4757:136"/> good &amp; Godly men, of whom no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng is heard, but that is good and Godly,
ſoundyng alwaie to goodnes.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Demas ſaluteth you.) This Demas, when Paule wrote this Epiſtle to theſe
Coloſſians, doth here appere, not as yet to haue ſhrynked awaie from Paule, or from his
doctryne. Therefore in the Epiſtle to Philemon (whiche dooth appere, to haue been writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of
Paule, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he wrote this Epiſtle) he calleth Demas an helper to hym, but when Paule was caſt
in priſon, and in daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of his life, for the Goſpelles ſake, then al left Paule, and this
Demas conueighed hymſelf, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waie from Paule, as it is writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>ii. Timo. iiii.</hi> Saieth
Paule, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas hath forſaken me, imbraced
<pb facs="tcp:4757:137"/> the preſent worlde, and went to Theſſalonica. Learne in Demas that there be
many now a daies like to hym: as long as with Paule all thynges was proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, he was a
faithful miniſter to Paule, and a faithful diſciple of Chriſte, but when he ſawe Paule
caſte in priſon, he forſoke Paule and his doctryne, and fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the worlde, ſuche there be
in the worlde, that will be fauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers of Goddes worde, as long as pleaſure, profite, fauor of
me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, honor, glory, and riches, do fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe the worde of GOD, but if affliccion, perſecucion,
loſſe of gooddes, riches, landes, poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or ſuche other aduerſitie ſhould
followe the fauoryng of Gods worde, then many ſhryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth away from it, and foloweth
<pb facs="tcp:4757:137"/> the worlde, as this Demas did, of ſuche ſpeaketh Chriſte. <hi>Math. xiii.</hi>
Many for a tyme dooth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue, but in tyme of tribulacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, thei ſhrynke awaie. Therfore he that
ſtandeth, let hym looke that he fall not, let hym not truſte to muche, to his awne mighte or
power, for if he doo, he ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue hymſelf, and haue a fall as Demas had.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Salute the brethren, whiche are at Laodice.) He deſireth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſalute in his name,
the brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that are at Laodice, and Nym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pham, and the whole congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion or company, in her
houſe, whiche, he calleth a Churche: for a ſmall congregacion, of faithe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Chriſtians,
maie be called a Churche. Note that the whole houſe for the moſte parte, do fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uor
<pb facs="tcp:4757:138"/> the Goſpell of God, where as the chief of the houſe doo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uor it, as this good
Nimpha did fauor the Goſpell, with all her houſholde.</p>
            <p n="4">4 And when this Epiſtle ſhalbe redde of you, loke that the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, written from
Laodice, maie be redde emonges you, and this of the Laodicenſes.) The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle will this
Epiſtle, firſt, to bee redde emonges the Coloſſians, and then to the churche of Lao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice,
that all might here it redde, and be edefied by it, &amp; take ſome of the Godly leſſons,
taughte in it, and he willeth it to bee redde, bothe to the church of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Coloſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and of
Laodice: of the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che we may gather, the holy ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, not to be communicated onely, to one
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<pb facs="tcp:4757:138"/> but to bee mete for all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, that thei might come to ſaluacion, by
faithe in Chriſte, Alſo, where as Paule here wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, an Epiſtle of the Laodice, to bee
redde emonges theſe Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſſians, ſome thynketh that he would, the Epiſtle that he wrote
to the Laodiceans (whiche Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle I haue ſene in Print) to bee redde to theſe
Coloſſians. Other thynke, that he would haue red, emonges the Coloſſians, the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle
that he wrote at Laodice, and that thei ſaie, was the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d Epiſtle to Timothe.</p>
            <p>And tell Archippus, loke that thou take hede of that Adminiſtracion, that thou haſte taken
in the lorde, that thou maie
<pb facs="tcp:4757:139"/> fulfill it.</p>
            <p>Now laſt of all he moniſheth them, to admoniſhe Archippus, the Biſhop of theſe
Coloſſians, that he would loke diligenty v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon his cure, that he had taken in hande, that he
ſhould knowe, that it was the Lordes buſines, that was committed to him: and that of it he
ſhould geue a cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt to the Lorde, in the laſte daie. Learne that Archippus was a Biſhop,
appoynted to theſe Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſſia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, rather then to other, and not as Paule was a Biſhoppe,
hauyng like cure ouer all peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. And as it was Archippus duetie, to haue cure and care for all
his people, and diligently to watche, to doo his duetie, and to miniſter euery thyng in due
or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre, to the glory of God, and to
<pb facs="tcp:4757:139"/> the profite of other, ſo it was the duetie of theſe Coloſſians, to
mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter to Archippus, all neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries for his liuyng. <hi>i. Corin. ix.i. Timothe. v.
Matth. x.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Salutacion by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per hande of Paule: Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membre you my bondes. The grace of GOD bee with
you. Amen.</p>
            <p>Paule ſhutteth vp his Epiſtle ſealyng it with a ſalutacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by his awne hand, as
menne writyng Epiſtles vſeth to dooe, ſealeth the Epiſtle, ſetting to his awne hand
writen, that it might bee knowen, who wrote that E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle, and be the better loued.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Remembre you my bondes.) In theſe wordes he ſignifieth to theim, that he ſuffered
bondes
<pb facs="tcp:4757:140"/> for their ſakes, that thei ſhould walke in the waie of the Lorde, and obtein
eternall life, and that thei ſhould not bee aſhamed for his bondes, whiche was to the glory of
God, and to the healthe of Chriſtians. And in theſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, he moueth theim to pitie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
him, and that thei ſhould of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fre vp ferue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t praiers, to the lord for him, and that thei ſhould
not ſuffre hym, to want neceſſaries, ſeyng he was in bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des for their ſakes and
health.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The grace of GOD bee with you. Amen.) Laſte of all, he deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the grace of GOD,
and of our Lorde Ieſu Chriſt, to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waie preſent with theim. In de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiryng grace of God,
he beganne his epiſtle, and with deſiryng of grace to theim, he endeth his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle,
<pb facs="tcp:4757:140"/> ſignifiyng, that without the grace of God, wee can begyn no good woorke, nor yet
finiſhe it well, but by the grace of God, whiche would haue euery man ſaued, and come to the
knowlege of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth. To God the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and to his ſonne Ieſus Chriſte, with the holy
ghoſte, bee all honor, and glory, now and euer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:4757:141" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>EXCVSVM</hi> LONDINI, IN AEDIBVS RI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHARDI GRAF<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TONI, TYPOGRA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PHI REGII.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno ſalutis humanae. M.D.XLV.III.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>CVM PRIVILEGIO AD IMPRIMEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DVM SOLVM</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:4757:141"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
